The science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport, play, and
life. Welcome to
Perform. I'm Dr. Andy Galpet. I'm a
professor and scientist and the
executive director of the human
performance center at Parker University.
Today I'm going to be talking with my
longtime friend, Dr. Mike Ormsby. Mike
is a professor at Florida State
University. He is the director of the
Institute of Sports Science and
Medicine. Mike is a world-renowned
expert in all things exercise
physiology, supplementation, sports
nutrition, and a whole host of other
important and interesting topics that
we'll get into in today's conversation.
Mike has done a tremendous amount of
work over the last 15 years,
specifically in the area of pre-le
nutrition. And I could promise you,
we're going to get into some things that
are Mike's lifelong passion and career,
that are counterintuitive to what most
people think about what to eat and what
not to eat. prior to sleep. In fact,
I'll give you a little bit of a spoiler
alert. He has some pretty compelling
evidence over multiple studies that
eating specific items in specific
amounts prior to sleep is advantageous
for not only sleep and recovery, but
multiple other things as well. The
conversation was wide ranging, but we'll
cover many other things like a handful
of supplements that people have not
heard of that have interesting
implications for a wide variety of
performance and health related outcomes.
And so it was a fascinating
conversation. I learned a lot from it.
I've known Mike for a long time. I've
known his work for a long time, but
there was a lot that I did not know
about the work he's done and will be
doing in the future. So here we go with
Dr. Mike Ormsby. I hope you enjoy the
conversation as much as I did. Dr. Mike
Ormsby, thank you so much for coming
out. I know it was a long trip this
morning and I have a bunch of stuff I'm
excited to talk to you about, but first
thank you so much for coming out. You're
welcome. Welcome. I've not been able to
come over here and do some podcasting
and hang out on this side of the country
for a while. So, um, for me, it's a
pleasure. I appreciate the offer. I love
your research. I love a lot of the stuff
that you've gotten into. So, I when we
decided to officially have guests for
Perform, I was like, Mike Mike has got
to be on the list and stoked to have you
out here. Appreciate it. I can't wait to
get into some of this stuff because uh I
love it. It's it's what I do day in and
day out and um speaking to a bigger
audience is a pleasure. Fantastic, man.
We're going to go to a lot of areas, but
where I want to start is actually with
ultra endurance stuff. Sure. So, you
yourself, I know you played hockey uh
and probably plenty of other sports, but
then you not only have competed in
various forms of ultras and then you've
done a lot of research in that. So, like
tell me how you got into that background
and then like very specifically some of
the studies you've done. Yeah. And the
athletes you work with. So, yeah, I
played college ice hockey through my
junior year at Skidmore College in
upstate New York. Um, and then I went to
grad school in South Dakota and, uh,
coached the Peeweeb State Champs. Oh,
nice. Uh, out there, which was a great
opportunity to coach. So, that was like
my my dip into that a little bit. And
then, um, coming back to go to more
graduate school, I ended up um, uh,
being at ECU and they're like I saw an
email come across and it said, "Anyone
ever play hockey before?" for and I'm
like, "Well, I used to play a lot of
hockey." So, I remember emailing the
coach and just saying, "Hey, we're we're
uh I'm here. I'm in my PhD program, so I
don't know how much I can contribute.
Can I come out?" And he's like, "Yep,
you got to be on the team." So, um that
was a lot of fun. They dropped me off to
study all day, pick me up to play a
11:00 p.m. game. Um and that was a great
season. That was the end of my
eligibility. Ended up playing two more
or coaching two more years at ECU. But I
finished and was like, there's this void
with being competitive. And that came
out in for me in triathlon of all
things. And I kind of got into it
because of my master's adviser. I showed
up for a um an interview basically in
South Dakota and he put me on a bike.
I'd never ridden a bike more than three
miles and we went for like a 20 mile,
which doesn't sound all that long now,
but it was excruciating. Yeah. when I'm
out here trying to ride a bike and keep
up and I thought um if he can leave work
and go ride his bike then I better learn
how to ride a bike so that I can go do
it with him or get out of here and go go
train a little bit. So that got me into
cycling and then um one thing led to
another and I was training for short
distance and then um my wife and I sort
of got into some of the middle distance
triathlon ended up finishing my longest
were like these 70.3 half iron man
events and so that was it. I loved the
training. I just I loved setting it up,
figuring out what I needed to do to to
meet all the different goals and demands
I had um in terms of increasing V2 max
or being able to push thresholds or you
know what kind of pacing that I want to
pull. And then nutrition played a
gigantic role in triathlon which I was
you know obviously into nutrition and
it's often considered the fourth aspect
of triathlon. Oh right. And so I got to
really put to practice the textbook
recommendations that are given like what
is a cleaner sport than being able in
terms of like following a textbook to a
tea. So many other sports you can't
really do that and clearly there are
curve balls that can come in even with
triathon but it's pretty specific like
you know the distance you know the
length if you can get the temperature
correct you can pretty much eat
according to textbook on these things.
So, I started making videos about it and
trying to post those for my students and
um travel along with my first half iron
man experience and those went over
really well. Um, and it was just an
awesome experience to sort of feel what
that was like. And I loved the idea of
training and trying to get better each
day and and competing. Turns out I'm not
very good at
triathlon. So, well, I mean, context
here a little bit. If everyone was to
see your physique, they would probably
not picture you as a triathlon kind of
guy. Yeah. You know what's funny? And so
I lost about 25 lbs training for that.
So I normally sit on I don't believe 20
of that as muscle probably. Yeah, I lost
so much. But I was like per I was like
fueling. I was doing the creatine. I was
doing everything to try to save what I
could and I documented it all. So I
actually did okay. But um when I was
down like getting real low uh you know
my friends and my wife in particular
like I you can't get too skinny on me.
So yeah. So that you know was a change.
I was definitely um uh my body type is
not really built for triathlon, but I
tried to force it that way for quite a
while. Now, I know that I'm assuming
that led into why you did some of your
work in your lab in these endurance,
I'll call them ultras and tribes and
things like that. I know you've also
done and still coach athletes in in
various these sports. But before we get
to that stuff, do you remember off hand
any specific things you did? any food
items or amounts or timings or fluids,
supplements, anything that you took for
your own personal performances that made
you feel better? Yeah. So, I was
targeting 60 grams an hour of
carbohydrate, which is pretty typical.
Um, typical, but lower probably. Yeah. I
didn't want to go north 90, 100 where
they're starting to go now. Um, I knew
I'm not elite enough to perhaps do it. I
didn't also have the stomach training to
handle it. Um, and it wasn't a priority
for me at the time. I wanted to do
textbook so I could show my students
here's a textbook. Here's what we're
doing. So it was 60 grams an hour. Um
and that that was fine. So I was I was
doing that with like goos and gooctain.
They're usually 30 grams. I was taking
two of those an hour. Yep. Um then I had
fluids on the bike and I used uh a
product at the time that had protein in
it as well. Not for anything other than
maybe help save a little muscle over
these prolonged periods of of training.
So, those were some common things that I
was uh doing over that time. Today's
episode is sponsored by Element. Element
is an electrolyte drink mix that has an
ideal electrolyte ratio of sodium,
potassium, and magnesium, but no sugar.
Hydration is critical to performance,
both physical and mental performance.
Countless studies have shown that even a
slight degree of dehydration, even as
small as 1%, can lead to decreases in
physical output and mental performance.
We also know that electrolytes are
critical to proper hydration, which I've
been harping on for years. But you can't
do that proper hydration by only
drinking water. You need to get the
right amount of electrolytes in the
right ratios. And that's why I'm a huge
fan of Element. In fact, many of you
will probably remember that I featured
Element in my YouTube series on
optimizing hydration nearly 5 years ago.
I featured Element in these videos
because their blend of 1,00 mg of
sodium, 200 milligrams potassium, and 60
milligrams of magnesium really is unique
and different than any other electrolyte
on the market, and it has great
scientific support. I use Element
constantly, particularly when I'm
sweating a lot, and I routinely make it
a part of my client's optimization
programs. If you'd like to try Element,
you can go to
drinklmnt.com/perform to claim a free
element sample pack with the purchase of
any Element drink mix. Again, that's
drinklmnt.com/perform to claim a free
sample pack. Today's episode is also
sponsored by EightLe. Eight makes smart
mattress covers with cooling, heating,
sleep tracking, and more. I've
personally been sleeping on an eightle
mattress cover for years now and it's
absolutely glorious. I love it so much
that I hate traveling away from home
because it means I can't sleep on my
EightLe Pod 4 Ultra. As you'll hear me
talk about endlessly on this podcast,
there really is nothing you can do that
makes more of an impact on your health
and performance than getting tremendous
sleep. And getting great sleep requires
having your body temperature drop a
couple of degrees at night. And that's
hard to do on your own. The Eight Sleep
has been a gamecher for me because I run
hot at night or as my wife calls it, I'm
a furnace. If I don't have something
like an eight helping me cool down, I'll
wake up in the middle of the night
overheating and not feeling great. This
is something I've also found in many of
the people that I coach, especially
those who are really physically active.
The EightLe Pod 4 Ultra has two times
more cooling power, yet is virtually
silent. And it has highfidelity sleep
tracking and even has snoring detection
that'll automatically lift your head a
few degrees to improve air flow and stop
your snoring. If you'd like to try
eight, go to
eight.com/perform to save $350 off your
Pod 4 Ultra. Asleep currently ships to
the US, Canada, the UK, select countries
in the EU, and even Australia. Again,
that's
8.com/perform. I want to uh transition
from there and talk about one of the
areas you're probably most famous for,
and that is nutrition prior to sleep.
And I it has stunned me that despite you
talking about this and working in this
area for 15 plus years, yeah, I don't
know how many publications you have on
this, but it's it's not a small amount.
And very few people have either heard
this or put it into practice. I'm really
shocked because of how effective, how
well-rounded uh this has been shown, how
many different populations you've done
this with. And again, people somehow
completely either don't talk about it or
they give the exact opposite advice. So
on the spot right now, tell me exactly
what I should be eating prior to bed.
And I'm being a little bit facicious
there. So take this where you want to
take your area. 40 at this moment 40
grams of a protein dominant food that's
less than 220 calories. Okay. So what
you're suggesting is about uh most of
your studies have been 30 minutes,
right? So 30 minutes prior to going to
sleep, 40 gram bolis. And why on earth
would I do that? Yeah. So let me tell
you a story. And how does it not hurt my
sleep? Okay, so we'll get into all that,
but let me first tell you the background
on some of this. So stemming from those
Ultram man studies and our sleep was
sort of linked into this. So um if
anyone can remember those old shows were
giant weight loss shows on television
that existed for a long time. The the
the TV talking heads would always say
stop eat. There's a cut off time.
There's a cut off time. And I remember
being a grad student at the time or even
undergrad at the time and thinking well
everybody I know eats at night and
they're all very much fit and in shape
and have no problem. And so this this
dichotomy is going on. I'm thinking I
don't know. I I've never seen a paper on
it. I'd love to see that and started
looking at it a little bit here and
there. And then finally, you know, when
I was independent um investigator was
started on on that path. Was this your
first study that you did? First one at
Florida State at your lab. Yeah. First
one in my own lab at Florida State. We
we got some small um funding for it and
we decided uh let's see what happens.
And then 15 years later, we're we're
designing two new ones right now. So,
okay, let me let me take you on that
story. So, please. Yeah. So, uh that was
going on. People were saying, "Don't eat
at this time. Don't eat." I'm thinking,
"I don't know. There's I know a lot of
people plus in like the bodybuilding
circle, the figure world, people would
purposefully eat at night or they would
purposely if they had to wake up to like
use the bathroom, they'd have a protein
shake sitting right there in the
bathroom. I remember many days of having
pre-made protein shakes in the bathroom.
So, not only if you woke up, but I
remember setting an alarm to make sure
that I woke up, smashed the protein
shake, and went back and people
constantly did this. This is a very
common thing. It was it was super
common. So, there was just these
different worlds. And so, clearly, there
were like we got to start somewhere.
What what's happening here? So, we
started looking through the literature
and this was about 2010. Um, and there
was really nothing that existed in the
way that we're thinking about pre-le
feeding, what to eat before bed. There
was some data in large mixed meals like
having your fullon dinner before bed
late at night that weren't very good.
So, uh, 1993 Roman did a study where I
remember they gave 544 calories and they
gave you this in the morning, in the
afternoon, or in the evening. And they
just measured your metabolic response to
the meal. And it was it was just a stair
step. So, if you had it in the morning,
you had the best response. In the in the
in the middle of the day, you had a
medium response. If you had it at night,
you had a very low metabolic response to
that meal. So perhaps those that are a
little bit less versed in science would
be taking that study and saying, "Okay,
therefore, you'll be better
metabolically by having your calories
earlier in the day." Exactly. Yeah. And
in more to the story, but and in
reverse, they'd say if you had your
calories at night, you're going to get
fat. Bingo. You're going to gain weight.
So this is where that whole story
started. This is where it all started,
1993. And then several other things have
happened along the way. Um there was a
study in 2004 from Diccastro and that
looked at like when do you feel the
hungriest and when do you eat the
biggest meal and they're always in the
evening. Um and so all the data were
lining up that you're hungriest at that
time. Your uh ability to like control
your caloric intake is worse at that
time. And so so you'll be less
metabolically healthy. You'll make worse
choices. You'll probably overeat and so
everyone says you're going to have
you're going to have trouble. So but you
know I'm thinking of a protein shake,
right? And that's how we started. We
started giving. This is why meat heads
need to be in science. This entire this
is this is a meatthead thing. It really
is. And it's like co common sense is
like, well, I don't need 600 calories. I
just want a protein shake. What is that
going to do? Or scrambled eggs or
whatever it was that I was eating just
naturally at that time. So, we designed
designed a couple of studies at the at
that time. Um, very simple, great simple
design, simple answer. I give you a few
options to drink before bed. Uh like a
whey shake, a casein shake at 30 grams a
piece or a carbohydrate or a placebo.
And they all taste the same. They're
blinded. Um and so you go home, you take
this, you come back to me in the morning
and I measure your resting metabolic
rate. That's it. I see how your
metabolism may or may not change some
eight hours later. And so you come back
in the morning and if you had nothing,
so like the placebo, which was no
calories, you had a response where your
RQ was kind of low. So you're burning
more fat at that period of time as you
would. So not that you're burning more
or less calories, but the percentage of
your calories coming from fat. Correct.
Versus carbohydrates. Exactly. And
that's RQ. Same. And that was no
difference from the casein drink. So in
both cases with with in the first
studies um if you had either nothing or
you had casein you still had quite a
nice ability to burn a big percentage of
fat the next morning. And then when we
gave the whey that was pretty close but
not quite there in terms of how low or
the RQ was how how good the fat burning
was. And then carbohydrate was a little
bit worse than that. Um, but nothing was
bad and everything seemed to show an
improvement over having no calories at
all in terms of the total metabolic rate
the next morning. But so many holes in
that, right? So, we got hammered from
reviewers. I remember, oh, I'm so proud
of this. And then it came back. It's
like, well, you didn't do this, this,
this, this. As you were saying that, I
was in my head going, I
I'm going to ask, okay, okay, okay. So
many problems. Okay, I got the comment
section. I got you guys. Yeah. And so
what we first study, first the first
one, the very first one, guys. and we
wanted to see how that reacted and that
was in um that was in sort of young men.
Then we looked at this in different
populations. So we started to go to
different populations. We started to
look at um overweight women and then um
some women with obesity and we repeated
the study and had very similar outcomes.
So casein and whey being quite favorable
for metabolic rate in the morning. Um
what the problem we had was we hadn't
introduced exercise yet. So we didn't
know what that was doing and we have no
idea what you're what's happening from
leaving my lab with a shake in your hand
to coming back to me the next morning.
So a series of more studies we designed
uh I know 15 more after that along the
way where we ended up putting mattresses
in the lab and having people sleep there
so that we could just monitor
everything. We ended up thinking about
um uh exercise in a way that was useful.
So one of those studies in ob with women
with obesity in the beginning they had
actually a rise in glucose and insulin
um from having the the shake before bed
when we measured it the next mornings
and that's not a good thing. You don't
want that to be so we decided to
introduce exercise minimally uh I think
it was two days a week we put in and we
just did it for four weeks but when we
did even just a little bit of exercise
with people who didn't usually do it all
of those negative things went away
entirely. It just shows you how powerful
exercise driving all of this stuff um
over the nutrition. I mean, any day that
exercise base is going to be the main
mover of the physiological needle and
the nutrition really just helps push it
one way or the other.
Um, the other thing we didn't uh do well
was that if you're sleeping at home or
sleeping in the lab, um, how do I know
how if that's like your usual way of
sleeping and does that influence fat
metabolism? So, I remember a reviewer
said, "Did you measure sleep?" I'm like,
"Never even crossed my mind." And I'm
doing sleep. I'm doing pre-leep studies.
So, at that time, we just implemented
like a survey. So, you come in and we
say, "Okay, how much uh, you know, how
much did you sleep last night? Was it
good or bad or usual? And then in that
simple measure, we saw no differences.
And then we brought them into the
laboratory. We're like, "Oh, well,
surely that's not going to be great for
sleep. It's a different environment and
all these things." And we made it again
pen and paper. No difference in what
we're finding in terms of just asking
them that question. And so then we now
I'll fast forward to kind of what we're
getting to in in a few minutes, but now
we're purposefully designing for an
outcome of sleep where we've never done
that before. We've always measured it
for recovery. We've measured it for
metabolism, not for the outcome of sleep
as our primary aim, but we'll talk about
that in a second.
Um, one of the things that I think
really helps us now is that we
introduced in some of our studies a
technique called
microdialysis. Now, that's something
that I learned in grad school from uh a
guy named Professor Bob Hickner. Great
friend, excellent researcher, my mentor,
uh just a phenomenal human. I visited
his lab a couple of times a long time
ago, but a ton a ton of great work over
the years. So, yeah, consistently just
excellent work. And you eventually drug
him down to hang out with you in Florida
State. I did. Yeah, that's a whole
another story. It's uh but it's
fantastic because I have like the
godfather of microalysis in our backyard
and it's it's great and that's a
technique I learned in my PhD program as
well. So, we started implementing this
microalysis. You walk us through what
that is really quickly. Yeah. So, it's
exactly what it sounds like, but yeah,
it it is, but yeah, I guess it's a
little complicated. So, imagine like u
getting your belly pierced. So, when we
originally started this, it was you
pinch a roll of fat in your sub your
subcutaneous fat on your on your belly
and then you'd put a small needle
through and then pull it out the other
side and it's threaded with um a tiny
probe, a flexible membrane that you can
slide underneath the skin. So, then the
needle is out entirely. You just leave
this little flexible tubing under the
skin. Um, luckily now they make these as
concentric probes. So, it's only one
poke instead of two. So, you'd only have
to pinch and put one um, poke in there.
And then what happens is there's an
inlet tube and an outlet tube, tiny
little micro tubes. Um, and then you can
say you can peruse all kinds of stuff,
but we peruse saline and saline goes
into the interstitial space and mixes
around and then comes out the outlet
tube. So what I measure should be saline
plus whatever is coming out of the cells
around the probe. Um and so we measure
in that probe real time um all kinds of
stuff. But traditionally glycerol is the
primary marker we're looking at for fat
metabolism. So specifically lipolysis,
right? So what you're doing is you're
putting a small needle in somebody's
belly fat so you can measure exactly how
much fat is being burned. Right? The the
other way to do it is you collect the
gases that they're breathing out of
their mouth. Yeah. But slightly
different. But slightly different. So
the oxidation piece is a little bit
different. We're looking specifically at
lipolysis. We have no idea if it's
actually being burned. It's just being
liberated from the cell, right? And so
we'll pick that up in the probe and we
have to measure that. So um adiposytes
lack the enzyme glycerol kynise and so
glycerol can't go back into the
adiposite and so it is a little more
stable than measuring free fatty acids
for example because they can a little
more readily go in and out of the fat
cell in certain conditions. Um so
glycerol is the main marker of
lipolysis. So really quickly what does
glycerol have to do with fat? Right? So
you've heard of a triglyceride.
Everybody's probably heard of that. So
the backbone of uh of a triglyceride tri
being three or three fatty acids
attached to a glycerol and so that's
liberated through hormone sensitive
lipase as the adiposite is um stimulated
to release fat and that can be from all
kinds of stuff but exercise is typically
what we we use to drive that and then
you'll they'll all be liberated from the
cell and eventually glycerol will be
also put into the inner social space and
ultimately we can pick that up in the
microialysis um dialysate that we
collect, right? So, what what you're
able to look at is directly from the
tissue. Whereas, if you're on a
metabolic cart and measuring gases, it
still sounds and feels like you're
measuring fat burning, but as you said
earlier, you're not. One is measuring
the entire body and how much actual
carbon dioxide you're breathing out. And
what you're measuring directly is how
much, and if you're not familiar with
this is lipolysis. This is the breakdown
of fat. And you mentioned this quickly,
but really making sure folks don't miss
it. Fat burning and fat loss and fat
oxidation are not necessarily the same
thing. They sound similar. This is where
we can get lost in science a little bit,
but it's really important if you're
going to make a claim about what happens
to somebody's fat burning with, in your
case, what you eat before bed, measuring
directly in the tissue itself is going
to give you a significantly different
answer than measuring resting metabolic
rate or on a car or something. Yeah. And
what's what's nice about this technique
is that we're describing it in the
abdominal fat Yeah. tissue. So people
care, but we also can do it right now
like we're running a study where we're
looking at the abdominal and we're also
looking at the glutial and men and women
have different amounts of fat in those
areas and it all has to do with the
receptor type that's on the adiposite in
that space. And so we have like these
beta and he has alpha receptors that
primarily drive what's going on in these
different spaces. And so you and I will
have a different concentration of the
alpha and beta receptors on the adipite
in our abdomen versus our hips and and
top of our buttocks, right? And so women
will also have a different profile. Um
and that also changes to like for
example the permenopause menopause
transition. Um a lot of those things are
are are really interesting for people to
know like what's going on these
different tissues. Can we fix it? And
then we can also put drugs through the
probe if we need to and we can stimulate
or inhibit those receptors and figure
out mechanistically what's going on in
the different tissues. Um but for our
pre-le feeding studies we weren't
profusing any drugs. It was just simply
looking at what was going on with
lipolysis and then we would measure
oxidation with the breast samples as
well. So you have to do both. Um but it
gives you a better picture of exactly
what's happening. Um so we finally had
this tool to measure glycerol. So
lipolysis overnight and I remember my
doctoral student at the time um Amber
Kinsey was my first doc student running
this this study and I remember she came
in and she's like oh my goodness um
nothing happened like we like we we
didn't see any difference in lipolysis
no matter if they took carbohydrate
protein placebo whatever we gave and uh
I I didn't I thought we'd see something
and I remember going through the data
and we're like you know what this means
you can have something before bed and it
does not change
lipolysis. So, you don't have to worry
about the fat metabolism piece of this
with a small uh calorically small meal
or or protein shake and a protein
dominant situation. So to tie that
together, if the 1993 paper held true
and the follow-up paper held true and
eating before bed was going to make you
fatter, what you should have saw in your
study is you should have saw the rate of
lipolysis go down, right? You should
have seen less fat burning. We're going
to refer to it like that. But when you
saw that it didn't go down, it stayed
the same. This is actually the powerful
conclusion that that meal you had before
bed did not make you fatter and did not
at all alter your fat burning either
ability overall or the rate at which
you're doing it. Correct. I have had the
scenario with totally different topics
multiple times in my lab with my
students where they come in freaking
out. My thesis didn't work. My
dissertation failed. Yeah. And you have
to really step back and say what is the
data telling me? In your particular case
it was potentially and one would argue
more powerful the fact that it wasn't
different. Yeah, and I agree it's it's
really hard in uh doing research in this
space
because everybody wants to find the
magic pill or potion or situation and
there are very few studies where we find
some kind of amazing claim that comes
out of it. Almost every time we're
saying no that didn't work and that
didn't work either. That didn't work
either. Um and it's really it's a fun
process to be on. beautiful thing is
that that's equally as important in our
field for people to know that. Um there
are some fields where sort of quote
negative data would be a big problem,
but uh that's not the case here because
it's really important people know if
something works or doesn't and and
depending on what outcome you're looking
at. Yep. Um let me go back to a little
bit of the pre-le protein story. So we
were one of two labs doing this work
from the early stages. So the other lab
was Luke Vanlon's lab. Oh, sure. and
Mastric University and their work is
fantastic. And so protein synthesis guy
big time, protein synthesis. So what
Luke's group was doing was looking at
pre-le feeding all from a muscle protein
synthesis perspective where we're
looking at it more from a fat oxidation,
fat mobilization, applied outcomes
perspective. And so it was really fun.
Several times I've teamed up with Luke
to give um talks at different
conferences and things where we cover
all aspects of this prele feeding. We
probably do for a new one at some point.
a lot of new data have come out for but
for about 10 years we were the only ones
doing that work. Now it's like every
week I find a new paper on the topic
which is really exciting. It's it's um
rapidly expanding our knowledge base.
They're all citing your papers every
time. They they they prefer the muscle
protein synthesis ones for sure but it's
really good work. And what Luke found
out was that for a while we didn't even
know if you could have muscle protein
synthesis at that period of time. No one
had ever done it. Um so he was giving
young men and older men protein
bololises and then they were doing lines
and biopsies through the night and the
next morning and things and um man one
of those had like nasogastric feeding to
get the protein in that way in these
older individuals. So study after study
after study showed, okay, yeah, you can
feed at that point and have an increase
in muscle protein synthesis. And their
studies are awesome and they've done so
much good work over the time. And so
mixed with our data, it looks like we're
in a place where it's either not going
to do anything pre-le feeding or you
could have an improvement in muscle
protein synthesis and perhaps recovery
in some of these other areas and maybe a
change in metabolism that will be
beneficial for some people. Um, at the
very least, you're creating an
opportunity to meet your total daily
protein goals. And almost every paper in
the last six years that we've written
ends with that. It's probably most
important as a feeding opportunity
simply to heat hit your protein targets
for the day. Secondarily, and it's
probably a big secondarily, is it could
specifically be useful at that time of
day, but it's primarily driven by total
protein intake for the day. um minor
benefits may come from it. The best
example of that's from Luke's lab, uh
Snider's study. Um and they actually did
12 weeks of training with a pre-le
feeding protocol. And the they had
carbohydrates and protein in a in a
shake. And they did this for 12 weeks
and they actually had functional
outcomes. So not just MPS where you're
not sure if muscle will actually grow.
Yeah. Instead of just looking at muscle
protein synthesis, they Yeah. Not just
the marker, we're looking at the actual
outcome and did you actually get bigger
muscle? and they found improvements in
CS cross-sectional area. They found
improvements in strength like 1RM. Um,
all things people would be interested in
simply by having a a pre-sleep shake.
Um, the interesting part was that study
was criticized because there were
different total amounts of protein taken
between the groups. And so the group who
had pre-le protein had 1.9 grams per kg
and the group who had uh didn't take the
pre-le protein had 1.3 grams uh per kg.
So there was a difference. now both
north of the recommended 0.8 grams per
kg. Um, and they were criticized for it,
but they're they're, you know, the way
they thought about it was no, no, it's
just a feeding opportunity. Take it.
You're at home. You have access to these
foods. You don't have to be afraid of
it. Um, and in our in their hands, it
worked. Increasing the total daily
protein intake. You digested it. You
absorbed it. And you actually laid on
muscle with it. So, you said quickly a
second ago, 0.8 Eight grams per kg is
the recommended. It you mean as in what
you recommend or in No, no, no, no. Uh,
okay. Yeah. So, clear clarify. Yeah. So,
RDA, the recommended um allowances is
0.8 grams per kg to start to stave off
issues that can come from lack of
protein. Um, and so that number, you
know, it's pretty contested by people
who work in this space, although it
keeps coming up because it is a number
that probably will stave off problems.
Um, we typically, I mean, there's so
much data on here. I'm sure you'll have
speakers directly in this area, but it's
it's it's just incredible. Like, we
usually recommend up to a gram per pound
or 2.2 grams per kg. Most people don't
hit it and they land right at 1.6 1.7,
which is right where I want them. Yeah.
Um, and so that number works for us.
We've had success with that in our
various other protein feeding studies,
but um there's a tangent I'd love to get
on if we want to. Uh so we we've done a
lot of protein feeding studies of people
with uh obesity. One of the ones that I
thought was very interesting and I think
your your audience will like it too. The
we were looking at morbidly obese
individuals going for beriatric
surgery. So when they show up at the
beriatric center instead of going in and
getting the consult and getting the
surgery scheduled, they find our team of
researchers in the front door. You know
how many people wanted to join us? Not
many.
Not many. But some said they'd try. And
so we had a few subjects trickle in over
time that would give us a try. So the uh
recommended um intake, calorie intake on
a on a medically prescribed beriatric
diet is extremely low. They're rough.
Very, very low. And now I say what,
thousand calories? Is that? Yeah. At the
time we did this, it was 800 calories
and it was primarily liquid, but there
was some options. Now, this was a few
years ago, so maybe it's different now.
I haven't looked at it lately.
What we did is we took these
individuals, we put them into two
groups. Um, we actually put in the IRB
that we didn't think was ethically
responsible to not give both groups more
protein. Yep. So, we did and they
approved that. So both groups got added
protein bowls which bumped them up to
almost 1,300 calories
roughly. One of those groups got
resistance training. Ah, one of them had
standard of care and the standard of
care was some directions on a piece of
paper or you can come in here, move some
tables around, do some calisthenics type
exercise. If you did 12 weeks of
resistance training and this was run by
Eddie Joe who's a professor now and his
um his major professor was D. Oh, was
this his dissertation? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
and uh his mentor was Cal State For was
Dr. Kim and Dr. Kim is a phenomenal man
who just recently passed away and his
they designed this whole deal. We were
giving him more protein and what was
astonishing uh was that before the study
began if you did off grams per kg which
how much protein they took in they were
down like 0.3
0.4 grams per kg because their body
weight is just a lot larger. Yeah. Um
after the study both groups over 12
weeks lost a ton of weight as you would
imagine. not eating much. Mhm. But if
you added resistance training, the
amount of uh according to Dexo, the
amount of muscle or lean mass that you
lost, so there's some issues with that.
We'll just call it same thing for now.
Yeah. Was
25% if you didn't train and was only 4%
if you did resistance train. So, so
translation, the group that didn't lift,
if you didn't lift, you lost a ton of
muscle. And and if you did, you lost
almost almost almost nothing. Four 4%.
You're going to lose some on that kind
of a diet and you just think about like
weight recidivism and the the people who
are probably going to struggle with this
and now you're at a place with lower
lean mass and you still have trouble
with these things and you're still
working on being taught the right things
to eat in this process. So to me that
was a fabulous study that really showed
the powerful uh impact that resistance
training with protein can have. you will
see
regularly strength training for folks
that are trying to lose weight and to
keep it off for a long time. So you said
that the retention recidivism of of that
body composition. You can't make a
strong argument that strength training
burns a ton of
calories. We were talking about that
before we started going like that's not
your way to go. One could even argue
then or people have used that argument
then as a fodder to say that hey
exercise doesn't help you lose weight.
completely ridiculous of course, but
from a strictly caloric expenditure
perspective, it's not very high.
However, if you look at that side of the
equation, who holds more muscle mass?
And then because of that, the
associations between strength training
and successful long-term and permanent
weight loss is really, really high. And
we've seen this from a bunch of
different lines of research. That paper
specifically, I think, just absolutely
crushed that conversation. If you want
to lose weight and keep it off, strength
training is a very, very, very good idea
if you want that to last for a long
time. It's not going to be the thing
that burns you your calories right now.
Yeah. But it's the thing that is going
to arguably lead to longer uh term
success. Yeah. I think if if if if you
skip that part of a weight maintenance
or even a weight loss program, it's just
not setting you up for the ideal ideal
outcomes long term. But it is it is hard
because you you do like if you're going
out for a walk or jog or a bike like you
sweat and then you feel like maybe
you're doing more work and so then you
get in your mind about maybe this is
better for me for my goals and it's it's
hard. I think you have to be disciplined
in many ways but to follow a program
where you're training and maybe not as
sweaty as you might be from doing you
know a run or even a walk outside or
something. So yeah, I feel like in our
in our uh environment now, we need to be
probably medically prescribing
resistance training at the root of all
this and that's just not happening yet
in most places. I know some folks are,
but um I think that's the next step
that's going to have to be taken.
Today's episode is sponsored by
Momentus. Momentus makes the highest
quality supplements on the market,
period. Many of you know me and you know
that I do not trust the vast majority of
supplement companies and for good
reason. Many studies have shown that
anywhere between 10 to up to 40% of
supplements have accidental
contaminants, intentional alterations,
mislabeling, or other serious issues.
But Momentus is different. I literally
spent years vetting the company, their
products, and leadership team before
personally officially partnering with
them in 2023. Every single one of
Momentus' products is third-party tested
to ensure quality, and many are even NSF
certified for sport. Now, while I love
all of their products, the ones I use
the most, both personally and with my
clients, are what I call the big three.
And these are the omega-3 fish oil,
creatine, and newly improved whey
protein formula. These three supplements
have fantastic data supporting their
benefits. Whey protein for lean muscle
mass, omega-3s for brain health, and
creatine for both muscle and brain
support. and they have been shown to be
very safe across basically all
populations of people, young, old, men,
women, etc. Now, nobody has to use
supplements, and I hope you never feel
pressured to do so, but if you're
interested in supplements, it's
important that you get them from the
highest quality providers. You don't
want mercury in your fish oil or lead in
your whey protein or anything like that.
So, that's why I stick exclusively to
Momentus. If you'd like to give Momentus
a try, go to live
momentous.com/perform to get 20% off
your order. Again, that's live
momentous.com/perform to get 20% off.
One of the things that is tough for
folks not in science to understand often
is how is the same response going from
kind of low to medium, not the same as
going from medium to high or high to
ultra high and things like that. Like we
see that physiologically consistently.
So, you're mentioning uh I think Luke's
study had a couple of different groups
and neither one of them are what we
would call maxed out on their protein.
So, neither one was at 2.2 grams per
kilogram, which is what you said you
personally recommend, right? Yeah.
So, what's important to
understand, if you take somebody who's
probably on a more traditional protein
diet, 04.5 maybe, and you increase that
person to one, is that going to be the
same response if you take somebody who's
at 2.2 already and take them to 2.5? No,
definitely not. Yeah. That when you're
under a certain threshold,
in this case, protein requirements,
right? Yeah. for protein requirements,
you're going to be you just have so many
winds to catch by getting up right to a
number that's north of 1.1 1.2. Um, and
honestly, that's really hard for some
folks. So, we have to be easy on
ourselves if you fall in that category.
Like, really work at trying to fit these
foods into your into your daily
practice. And I get it if you're busy,
you got kids, you got jobs, you got
things to going on, like that takes some
planning and that's a little bit of a
headache at first, but it's worth it.
like like they say the juice is worth
the squeeze because there the outcomes
are just really really nice. I mean
we've done so many studies and in my lab
or in collaboration a lot with Paul RCO
who's done a ton of this kind of work we
we've shown time and time again that the
higher protein loads help a lot with all
these goals we're talking about
particularly weight management um on
that side of it. I mean Stephan Pacio
did a study years ago that was the RDA
0.8 or double at 1.6 six or triple,
right? And so when they did that, what
was really nice to see was that double
was far better for the outcomes that
they were looking at in that paper, but
three times was not. And they landed on
double, which is 1.6. And so that's kind
of where we're landing with this. We've
done work in our space where we did 40%
of the diet as protein. And then we've
done um um some that we looked at 25 and
25 and 40 weren't all that much
different from each other. Um, although
I do think I've listened enough to like
Don Layman and these guys, I don't know
that protein should be a percentage. It
should probably always be at grams per
kg and then just set that as your anchor
for your meal planning and then work
around it. Yeah. Figure out your fueling
of your carbohydrates and your fat based
on how many calories you need, but keep
the total amount of protein there as
close as you can. Yeah. Yeah. So when
you when we when we kind of come back to
the end of the where we at now 15 years
of research on protein
or well all nutrients prior to sleep
pre-leep feeding
when we look at what Luke's group has
shown collectively and what your group
has shown let me see if I can summarize
this and correct me uh potentially a
benefit to muscle protein synthesis
which would potentially increase actual
muscle growth actual muscle strength.
Now, that's probably going to have the
biggest impact if your protein intake is
moderate to low. Right. Right. And this
is where going from 04.5 up to 1.2 or
1.5. We're getting closer to
1.6. And Luke and and yourself have said
this is all we're doing here is there's
nothing magic. There's nothing special.
There's no growth hormone release. We're
It's not a testo. It's just the fact
that you're getting another opportunity.
Yeah. To eat and hit your protein mark.
Yeah. If you're already at those markers
though, you're already at 1 gram per
pound or 2.2, then that pre-sleep
additional protein may or probably won't
add any additional to just Luke's side,
the muscle protein, right? Did I
summarize that? Yeah, that's probably
where we are at the state of it. And I
would say that's the first third of the
of the story. Yeah. Great. So, let's
finish that Luke and we'll talk muscle
growth sort of later. your your areas is
more interesting to me right now, which
is in addition to that though, you can
do that while not
compromising fat burning. So, you're
going to potentially gain some muscle
there and then you're not going to
there. So, I have a handful of questions
here. Specifically, I want to get into
details. What type of protein, what
other stuff, what population does this
work in men and women, young and old? I
want to get into um uh other areas of of
of like I said age. Um and then finally,
one thing we actually haven't really
talked about is you have said it doesn't
hurt fat burning. Does it do anything
good? Do we have any data that suggests
it does anything positive besides maybe
helping me hit my protein goal? So
number of things I'm going to run you
through here. U take me whichever one
you want to start there and I want to
make sure you don't miss any. Well, I
think to summarize that first bit that
like you just did, I think everybody
would agree that we should think of it
as the as another opportunity for a
protein
feeding. In an athletic context, we got
to remember that
sometimes pre-le feeding isn't just a
luxury, it's a requirement. It's the
only chance we have. Yes. And that's
what's missed. And I see a lot of times,
you know, I'll comment on these if I
ever see them, but this like don't eat
before bed. Even still, you're getting
it because it compromises sleep. And
we'll talk about that in a little while,
but there's so much context and there's
so many nuances that are needed to to
say that. So, let's talk about Ultra Man
Florida. If you finish a race at 9 at
night, 10 at night, and you got a race
at 5, 6 in the morning, you better eat
at night. You're going to have no shot
at competing tomorrow. So, that's one.
Also, we got to think about day after
day after day. Athletes have to train or
practice. So, why not take advantage
when a lot of times we're underfueled
and have other issues around not eating
enough. It's just another opportunity. I
work with athletes in virtually every
sport in America. They almost all
compete at night and then you have to do
something afterwards and then you're
going to bed fueling. So, yeah. So,
there's there's like that general
context. I think the other piece of this
that we started noticing over time and
we haven't even talked about it yet were
performance outcomes. That's what I'm
saying. Tell me tell me the benefits
here. What what good am I going to get
out of this? You haven't sold me yet,
Mike. Yeah. So So the probably the one
that gets the most traction um is study
by Abbott and Abbott's group looked at
professional soccer players and they
played an evening match. Oh, I know.
Yeah. Yeah. And then they had protein
intake afterwards. And then they
measured um reactive strength index. So
they were jumping off a 30 centimeter
box then told to jump as fast as they
could once they hit the ground. This is
a standard metric a lot of sports
performance teams will do as a test of
daily readiness. Yeah. Performance. So
it's not an uncommon test for them.
They're probably doing it multiple times
a week the entire season anyways. I'm
sure. And the other one's real common
too is a counter movement jump. Yep. So
they did those two and and these are
professional soccer players, English
league I believe and they were they were
able to demonstrate over the course of
the next three days of doing these tests
after just the one dose feeding after
the game that they actually either
maintain or came back to normal faster
post game. And so for me that was a
recovery benefit. Totally. So in our
data until now we never looked at
recovery. We're looking at metabolic
outcomes and other things like that.
Several other studies have come out
around this time that show a little bit
of a benefit here, something around this
same space and then some said no
benefit. And so I had u one of my doc
students Pat Sarosino look into this and
he started notifying um or noticing in
the literature a pattern. I looked at it
with him and we were like you know
what's happening where it shows a
benefit is when you exercise at night.
Where it doesn't show a benefit is where
you exercise in the morning. And those
weren't the design of those studies. We
just pulled the methods out and started
looking at what time of day was this
happening. This is why it's so
important so important for students to
read all the papers and organize them
somehow. I'm sure you do this a
different way than I do. This is the
least interesting thing ever for people
who are not scientists, but I can't pass
this opportunity. Right? You have these
things in an Excel file. You have them
and you have every variable you can in
there. And I promise you, you open that
Excel sheet up and you will see massive
patterns going on. Every breakthrough
I've had, every great idea I've done
scientifically has become possible
because that exact thing. You notice a
trend, you're like, "Oh my gosh, four
studies, seven studies, nine studies,
and it oftentimes it lines up and that's
where you can actually see things that
you will never be able to notice that in
a single study." You have to have a
command in the literature. So kudos to
you and your doc student for doing that.
And that's really interesting. Yeah. fat
pet definitely drove that one home and
so we decided to design a study around
it and simultaneously we were interested
in protein type. So that's what we did.
We took middle-aged men, go figure. Um
and we wanted to see how they responded
to pre-le feeding after after some
damaging exercise. Um you know the
classic studies where you do some
eccentric exercises. Well, we took a
protocol that you get them as sore as
possible on purpose and we did. It's
really fun. And we and we did. And so
yeah, they had uh I think it was 150
eccentric only reps of extension and
flexion on the legs of their legs. Yeah.
Is this on a dynamometer, too? So you're
controlling. Yeah. This is a machine
that's going to hook your legs up and
force them uh you can control the force
output so they can't The pattern was was
So we triled it. Every everybody was
sore but made it through. And then um we
had some people start the study and we
ended up getting some people through and
then we had a couple cases where people
were like extremely sore. Yeah. And
these were even very fit individuals for
whatever reason. They had a couple of of
issues. And so we actually ended up
stopping that study short because of the
extreme amount of pain that they were
having. Um and they had we ended up
finishing with only six people per
group. And so the groups we had were uh
like a whey protein, um a a whey a
casein protein, a rice and pea combo. So
we wanted to look at a plant-based combo
and a placebo. Um and then we we damaged
them and then we controlled their entire
diet, the whole study. So it was like 72
hours after the damaging exercise. Yeah.
You gave them all their meals,
everything. Every single thing we gave
them. out. Obviously, it's human, so you
don't know what they sneaking in. But
that's a lot more controlled than most
would do. We tried to control. And of
course, then you get comments like, "Oh,
that wasn't that was too controlled.
It's not real life." But we tried to
control all these things. You're trying
to answer the question you're trying to
answer. That's that's how you desire.
We're trying to answer it. So, we we
damaged them so much that their markers
just dropped off, right? As you would
expect, like nobody could produce a
contraction that was anything. And then
it just never recovered. 72 hours later,
we were nowhere near back. Um, and in
almost every other study we had looked
at, you were at least close by 72 hours
later and we just never got there. And
so what we found, again, the type of
protein didn't matter in that case.
Everybody was too darn sore to actually
get back to normal in this particular
design. And so we just had to conclude
again like it didn't we had no
difference in protein type. So, that was
getting at your protein type question
was plant-based um didn't seem to matter
versus While we're here, let me linger
on this. I know you don't know the
answer because you haven't done these
studies yet, but if you were to guess
right now, then for most people, if
they're trying to get the performance
benefits you talked about earlier,
potentially the muscle growth. I know
that the recovery didn't matter in this,
let's say, frankly, pretty abnormal
training. Yeah.
Protocol. Okay, fine.
Do you have do you think it's going to
matter if someone has not only protein
type whey or casein
uh or even food type? So if they have to
have a protein shake, can they have
cottage cheese or yogurt? Do you have
what would you guess is going to plant
protein specifically is also very I love
this question because we we I'll give
you two stories here. The first one is
the story of our cottage cheese study.
So we were always wondering these like
whole foods things and we at the time it
was still thought that casein would be
the only like the best way to go because
of its slow digesting kinetics and
everything that we see during the day.
Our entire childhoods we've been told
casein is a slower releasing one. That's
the one to take before bed and yes and
so Luke and I had conversations about
that because we think it might be
different when when you're sleeping
because you're laying supine and it's
subtle changes in pH to your stomach and
these different things that are
occurring. Um, we just kind of had a
hunch on it and I'll give you the answer
because they actually ran this study um,
recently. Um, but the cottage cheese
study was great. Went to the
supermarket, pulled off a um, tubs, a
tub of it, and then I sent one to a
manufacturer to exactly exactly
replicate it in a powder, the macro, all
the profile. And so then I had a
semi-olid cottage cheese and a liquid to
compare it to and a placebo. Wow. And so
that was a neat studies we get at like
the consistency of the food and what is
that doing with these outcomes. And what
we saw in that one was again no
difference. The cottage cheese was not
different from the profile when you made
it into a shake. Um and so those two
were not different from each other. All
different from um placebo and well not
all. And some of the outcomes they were
better. Um and sleep we did measure in
this one. We put on um some watches to
measure sleep in this one. Again we saw
no differences in sleep. And so real
basic design looking at if we have a
semiolid or or or a liquid and and there
were no differences there. So it turned
out casing maybe isn't the only one or
the best one. And so
um Luke Vanlon, Yorn Tromalin and
colleagues put together a nice study
looking directly at um casein versus
whey and they looked at uh mitochondrial
MPS and myofhribral um MPS. And there
were no differences in pre-le feeding
with taking either the way or the case.
Yep. In any of the ways that you can
measure protein synthesis directly out
of muscle and they're very good at it.
Yeah, that's just worldleading. Yeah.
And so that right there was it because
some people don't like the the
consistency of cottage cheese. They
don't like the consistency of a casing
shake. They're different. Yep. Um and so
mouth feel makes a big difference. If
you don't want to drink it, you won't do
it. So um if someone says, "I love
caseine, I'm go for it. Someone go for
it. It doesn't seem to matter protein
type. It doesn't seem to matter whole
food or supplementation."
You've mentioned this a little in
passing, but I want to be really clear
here. You've done the assessment on men
and women. You've done it in folks with
obesity, folks that are young and
well-trained or you or other groups have
done this. I'm going to kind of
summarize the whole field here. It's
been done in young 20 25 year old
college age folks, middle-aged. Has it
been done in an older population like 60
plus? 70 plus. 70 plus.
any reason to think this answer changes
with any of those demographics or is it
generally consistently saying the same
thing?
Generally, it's saying the same thing
from everything that I've done been a
part of or read. I'm sure there might be
a study here and there slightly
different, but generally it's the same.
Um, unfortunately, one of my own studies
contradicted the time of day thing.
Yeah. Uh, we did that with Andrew McKun.
This is science. Okay. in Australia, but
we had some limitations to that study
with time of day of exercise and
performance. Um, but in general, what
you're saying is accurate. One of the
interesting things about this is it
keeps evolving. There's still a couple
things we don't know and we're trying to
work on it.
So, one of the things we've done over
this time is given oneoff feeding and
we've usually had sleep as a secondary
ter or tertiary aim if at all. And so we
finally designed one for sleep
specifically. And the thing we've done
this time is we're giving three nights
in a row of the feeding instead of one
night so that if you have an off or an
on night just by chance, we're not
picking it up as artifact that we can
hopefully, you know, get a better number
of nights involved with this. And it's a
lot of work because there's nighttime
things involved. We can help you on that
sleep front. Let's go. There's a lot
better ways to do that. So we're doing
that right now and we're doing that in
division one female athletes which is
fantastic. So that's ongoing this um
this whole academic year. So we should
have some answers on that on that next
year. We also put a CGM on them so we
can continually monitor how glucose
fluctuations are occurring through the
day and through the night um over this
period of time. Um and then the last
thing I'll say about that which is
really uh I think the way that it's
going there's a new player in the
protein world in pre-le feeding. Oh, and
uh is this breaking? Are you putting it
on perform? This is the first out about
this. It's not um it's new to this
space. So, it's being marketed for
sleep. It's called
alphalactylbin. It's a again
fractionated from dairy protein. Now, I
was unfamiliar with it and it's actually
very common. It's in mother's milk and
so it's in infant formula powders and
it's high in tryptophan. M and so
linking those together, someone said
high tryptophan, baby's sleeping, maybe
adults sleeping, let's fractionate it,
bottle it on its own and give that to
people. And so there's already been two
studies on it. And both of those were
Australian rugby and both of those
showed a benefit on sleep outcomes. M so
we're running that study now uh with our
division one female athletes and
Alphalac will be one of ours to see if
it's actually um doing it or we'll then
like our other studies where there's no
difference in things but right now we're
excited about it because there was
evidence from two other studies and
we're just doing it a bit more
controlled and in uh in our approach to
it. So Alphalax kind of the new player
there. Okay, I think we're kind of
winding the story down. Uh couple of
things I want to clarify. You've also
mentioned adnauseium. At this point,
there is no reason to think a meal like
this should interfere with sleep. Of
course, if the individual person is
upsets their stomach, gives them acid
reflux or something, then that's a
really good point. We we have to you
have to know how you react to things.
The other thing is you take you could
potentially be taking a large amount of
fluid right before bed, right? If that
makes you wake up and urinate too much,
then it's probably also something you
would want to have a different form or
maybe try to have your protein intake at
different times. You don't have to fill
the whole shaker with water, right? You
can fill eight ounces and shake it a
little bit. Yeah. And uh so yeah, the
the sleep part of this is going to be
sort of the next big story. And we're
currently um in negotiations to to try
to run another study because there's two
things we're still missing. I want to
know if there's a difference between the
quality of the food you're taking or
not. So, could you have a a mixed
macronutrient profile that's still
relatively low in calories and how does
that compare to something that's like
ultrarocessed?
And so, that's one we're trying to run
next is to look at specifically what is
going on with the quality of the of the
nutrient profile. And the other one is
there is there a calorie threshold.
Okay. Perfect. Perfect.
That's where I think we need to go
because 544 in the first study seemed to
not be good. And we're going to try to
do like a 0400 800 and then um the idea
would be to if we can pull it off would
be to mask it and uh and probably put it
into something like a milkshake. Okay. I
got three final short follow-ups to this
one, but you led me perfectly into here.
I think I know the answer based on what
you just said, but at this point, is it
something special about protein? You
actually said your first study was
protein, it was carbohydrate, and it was
multiple forms of protein, and you saw
no difference between the carbohydrate
and the protein for the most part in
those measures that you had, right?
Yeah. Do you think it is the protein or
is it going to just simply be the fact
that is a small in your case easily
digestible? You have
pre-powdered small amounts, easy to get
through your stomach foods. If you had
to guess right now, it's going to be
clearly a combination of these. But if
is it the protein or is it the meal size
and digestibility?
Yeah, I it's probably Tell me the answer
to your new study that you haven't done
yet. I think that we're going to have
something to meal size and
digestibility.
Um, however, we don't know the answer
for sure. But just like some of the
other studies I described, we we
sometimes think we know what's going on.
You can and then you have to just do the
study to show it. So, I think we're
going to find something to the calorie
threshold theory. I would bet a lot on
that. Yeah. Simply coming from
especially with sleep. Yes. So, that's
where we get mixed results. If you look
at sleep data, if you do eat large
calorie meals before bed, sometimes it
does mess with sleep. And I don't think
it's fair to say eating before bed
messes with sleep. It's specifically
what are you doing before and a before
extra before sleep and what exactly are
you eating? Because I can tell you right
now having done this a lot if you give
people an easily digestible carbohydrate
high fiber and easily digestible protein
under a total amount of volume and
calories probably 300 or so. You rarely
have sleep issues. In fact, many many
times you'll see enhanced sleep. And one
of the one of the things that you'll the
biggest things you'll see is the next
morning inertia. So the groggginess you
feel when you wake up the next morning
is oftent times improved. Not in every
single person, but rarely have we seen
that hurt people.
Exceptionally, again, I may I get a
little heartburn from it. Things like
that. My stomach felt like a rock. Okay,
fine. But you have very small meals like
that. I I would I know where I would put
my money. I don't know what your day is
going to find, but I think you're on to
something there. I think we see it like
like you're saying in these in the
people we work with, but when we're
doing this in a study, we can really
control it and find out exactly what's
happening. So, that's where I think
we're going to go with it that there are
data like uh I think it was the
Falconberg study and they were looking
at all types of macros before bed and it
was like lower glycemic, higher fiber
and and protein actually were all
helpful with sleep. And so, those are
the things that we're really doing here.
That's what we'll be looking at in these
new studies if we can get them launched
with our grant funding. Um, and I feel
like that's probably going to be the the
answer. We're going to have a threshold
and probably a quality of food as well.
The the oddest question I ever got about
this was, does it mess with your teeth?
Yep, I can see that. And I thought, I've
never asked that question, but normally
I think people would have it and then
brush their teeth before bed. So, we
haven't gone down that pathway yet.
Pre-post teeth brushing. Yeah. Yeah, not
my area. Okay, the last little one and
then I want to make sure we wrap this
thing here.
Um, have you guys actually looked at
this in either a calorie controlled
throughout the day fashion or a
specifically non-calorie controlled for
long-term fat loss? So, okay, I get it.
You sold me. I might recover better. I
might grow some more muscle and my fat
oxidation rate the next morning maybe
won't change. Okay, you sold me. Yeah,
it won't hurt my sleep, blah blah blah.
But am I going to lose more fat? Am I
going to gain more fat? What do we know
about 8, 10, 12 weeks long? Yeah. So,
it's a little bit
um extrapolated from other studies we've
done where just by chance there was an
evening protein shake. Okay. Yeah. So,
one of the earlier studies, I think it
was a 2002 with RCRO, we were looking at
um it was an old program called Body for
Life that Bill Phillips Oh, sure.
developed. Yeah. So, we did the first
study on that. So, Paul got that grant
and I was the student in the lab helping
on that study and that one included um
six meals a day and three of them were
shakes. Sure. So, you had a mid-m
morning, mid-afternoon, and an evening
protein shake. And then we did that for
12 weeks of training. And that training
was like three days a week of uh 20
minutes a hit, three days a week of uh
resistance training. So like six days of
exercise, it great. I mean really good
outcomes come were coming from that.
when that was compared to something like
the traditional American Heart
Association recommendations which were
definitely more carb heavy, definitely
less protein dominant and mostly um at
that point just physical activity like
walking, getting some more exercise
throughout the day. um when you had the
pre-le included in the total like
regiment you were following those folks
had far greater outcomes in terms of
abdominal fat loss, visceral atapost
tissue loss um and strength and actual
like performance outcomes over that
period of time. Okay. So would this be
fair to characterize the entire field
both your work and others as best we
know it now seems to be pretty
ubiquitous in terms of the groups the
population it won't matter postmenopause
premenopause young old so on and so
forth the type of protein perhaps
doesn't matter in that if you're already
hitting your protein targets then this
is not going to potentially have any
massive benefit but it doesn't seem like
it's going to harm much either if you're
already doing it probably okay if you're
already not doing it. You don't
necessarily need to go add this as long
as you're hitting your total protein
throughout the day. So, this is not
anything miraculous, but it is just
another option and it is perhaps most
importantly something people shouldn't
be afraid of. Absolutely. Yeah, that's
the biggest thing. I'm you I'm always
asked about it and it's it's really just
the exact thing. Don't be afraid of it.
If you're hungry, you have an option.
You can eat something and it's probably
gonna do either nothing or it will help
you. Really, really, really beneficial
when dieting. No doubt about that. If
you know you can turn to a 25 gram shake
at night and you're just the hunger
button is hammered to the bottom. Yeah.
Almost nothing is going to happen
negative in response to that 100%.
Today's episode is sponsored by AG1. AG1
is a vitamin mineral drink with
probiotics, prebiotics, and adaptogens.
Initially, I was extremely skeptical of
AG1, as I am with all supplement
companies. But after months of
discussions with their lead nutrition
scientist and the general team at AG1,
I've been impressed by AG1's commitment
to sourcing the highest quality
ingredients and constantly updating
their formulas to have the right
ingredients in the optimal amounts. By
now, it is abundantly clear that the gut
microbiome plays a critical role in
everything from body composition to bone
health to mental health. And the
probiotics and prebiotics in AG1 help to
promote a healthy gut microbiome,
improve digestion, reduce food cravings,
and increase short- chain fatty acids,
which play a critical role in regulating
metabolism and immune responses. It's
for these reasons and many others that I
personally take AG1 almost every day.
Now, it's of course not a replacement
for eating whole healthy foods, but it
is a great way to make sure that you're
plugging in any gaps in your nutrition
to improve your energy, bolster your
immune system, and just generally help
promote a healthy gut microbiome and
more. If you'd like to try AG1, you can
go to
drinkag1.com/perform to receive five
free travel packs, plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2. Again, that's
drinkagg.com/perform to receive five
free travel packs, plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus
K2. Well, thank you for giving such a
fantastic breakdown of of your 15 years
of work in the area of pre-leep and
probably most importantly justifying my
what is basically a nightly routine now,
especially when I'm on the road of I
absolutely smash a David bar before bed
all the time. literally never stop on on
the road. It's like dessert sort of
thing for me. But uh I feel justified
and what I'm hearing you say is there's
zero problem with that so I can continue
that habit. You got it from me.
Appreciate it. Uh I want to transition
from protein and talk a little bit more
about carbohydrate. You've done a lot of
work in this area as well and there are
perhaps more things we can learn here
that are counter to what uh other folks
have talked about or seen in the past.
So, uh, walk us through some of the
stuff you've done on specifically these
resistant
starches in your lab. Yeah, so we got
interested in
the modified carbohydrate space a while
back and it started with a a student who
was hyperinterested in carbohydrate.
Isn't that the best like Yeah. And they
drive I mean my lab is so fantastic.
They're they're all brilliant. They're
so much smarter than me and I love that
because they just have great ideas and
then we can weave it into stuff that we
can get funding for and it's it's just
it's just a really good mix. But I had
this u student at the time Dan Bower who
was phenomenal student and
hyperinterested in in all things
carbohydrate and I was kind of protein
dominant for all of the work I was into.
So it was a great addition to what we
were doing there to round out sort of
some of our macronutrient profiles that
we were interested in. Um he started
with a review paper that we sort of team
wrote to just get the history of what's
going on with these and if if you're
unaware of these modified starches um
well regular starch for example has
structural components of it like amalos
and amalopectin and they will dictate
the rate at which it will be digested.
When you modify that starch you do that
you can do it several ways chemically or
we were using hydrothermally modified so
it was like water and heat and pressure
and you can change it. um it it doesn't
matter any longer what the amalos
amalopectin ratio is, right? That's out
the window. It doesn't even matter. So
that's what students get tripped up on a
lot is that that once you modify it,
that's no longer a thing. Right. This is
the heat it up, let it cool back down.
Yes. Um and so the this the particular
product we started with was
um designed for people with glycogen
storage disease. Oh, Mardoles. So there
there's a glycogen separate too. There's
a outside of micardos there's glycogen
storage disease where you cannot store
glycogen and so what you have to do it
what what was developed was a a version
of this superstarch that was slow drip
didn't raise insulin and kept glucose
steady for long periods of time and so
that's how it was used for for a
different problem than breaking down
carbohydrate correct mardos right you
can't store it at all ah different
enzyatic problem yes still genetic I'm
assuming absolutely enzy Yeah. And so
what athletes do, they hear about this.
I what I love is that the clinical goes
to the athletes and the athlete kind of
work also goes to clinical. So I'm
thinking of cases like you know creatine
in athletes athletes over to clinical
and then in this case clinical with the
glycogen storage disease coming back to
athletes. So athletes here slow drip
glucose. Sure. Here we go. Uh some
companies got involved and they they
made a what what was called Ukan
Superstarch. Um and so we decided to
start testing it because there were a
lot of claims around it and um it was
just nice. We were able to really over
several studies decide um you know what
design do we need because the
superstarch folks would say that you
would need less uh of a of a serving
than you would of a normal carbohydrate.
So for example, if you normally have 60
grams per hour with the superstarch they
the claim was you could do maybe 30
grams per hour. You don't need as much
of it. this is slow drip and then it
wouldn't raise um insulin concentrations
either which I don't know that's a good
or bad thing but it just wouldn't do it.
Um and there were a couple studies on it
like Mike Roberts group did a little bit
with it which was how we sort of knew
about it. Um and we just sort of took it
another step. We used a microalysis
probes again and we started with
cyclists and so we brought in
well-trained they were very well
trained. They weren't elite but they
were very well trained cyclists. Um, and
so we put them through or Dan put them
through this gnarly protocol where we
made it as gut jarring as you possibly
could with interval sprints and all
these different protocols in a long
duration. Um, and we wanted to see 30
grams of it, which would be like a low
dose. And then we also gave 60 grams of
it because that's what was recommended
is 60 grams of carbohydrate. And then we
compared that to what's traditionally
used in a over- the-counter um sports
drink. So we compared it to other sports
drinks as well. And in the first study,
we saw that when you compared 60 grams
of the superstarch to 60 grams of the
sports drink, um the biggest trouble was
that the superstarch induced more GI
upset more. And the the unfortunately
the claims were that there were was
going to be less GI upset. In our hands,
we actually saw more GI upset. And this
is subjective reporting of cramping.
Yeah. It's like a like a visual analog
scale and it's a a 10point scale and you
mark a line with where you feel um and
nausea, um wanting to vomit, that kind
of thing. It was it was a tough
protocol. So, that's not good. Um and
performance, the outcomes we had were
actually not different. You just felt
terrible. M so like if you're talking
about rating of perceived exertion and
that can really dictate or limit like
how well you perform for sure uh you
think it's harder
but when we compared it to the 30 gram
dose which is what was typically
recommended like a lower dose you don't
need as much
um worse performance no GI upset but
worse performance so now you're in a
case where okay there's there wasn't any
G upset but you weren't taking enough so
you got the worst of both cases here so
yeah you got in this other case and so
at the highest dose if you train your
gut, then perhaps it was something that
you could use. Uh, but you could also
just use another sports drink and have a
similar response. I will say two things
about it though. A mistake that was made
perhaps that we did and could do better
was that we didn't familiarize people to
taking it. People were used to the
sports drink we were the other the
comparator, but they had never like had
it before. So perhaps we should have
given it for a while beforehand and then
tried it. Um, what are you giving this
in the form of liquid shake? Yeah,
liquid shake. It shouldn't be any
different. But nevertheless, that's a
comment that that we received. Um, I
don't know about that in that in that
front. So, haven't taken the reason I'm
saying that is I've taken a lot of
resisters in various forms and I've
never noticed a first time or or learned
effect of it. Yeah. You wouldn't think
so, but it's plausible. Sure. Yeah.
Plausible. Good scientist you are. It's
plausible. It's plausible. Um, the other
thing we wanted to see was maybe we
needed to jostle the gut a little bit
more and do running. So, in a follow-up
study for Dan's dissertation, he got two
dissertations out of this. Um, he went
after runners, elite runners, and some
of these runners were running like 14
minute 5ks and things. I look very very
fast after running for an hour at
marathon pace, you know. So, we it was a
good protocol again and we also put
microalysis probes in their belly while
they're running and doing all this uh
which is a feat in itself because
everything's jostling. So, you had to
tape everything down pretty good. Um
because we were also interested in what
fuel were being used and so Dan always
would say like just because um you can
change the fuel use should you? Sure.
You know, so you know, just like any
other feeding studies where you limit a
certain macronutrient or another, yeah,
you can change what's oxidized because
you're eating differently or you're
exercising at a different pace or what
have you. Um, and this was the same
thing with UK. Like, we could change the
fuel that was being utilized. And
insulin, by the way, didn't rise. So,
that claim was right. It it stayed low
and glucose stayed quite steady. You
didn't have any spikes or anything. So,
um, in the running study, it basically
mimicked the cycling study, even though
we were trying to jostle even more and
make sure we had GI upset if we were
going to see it. And it just ended up
being fairly similar. And the fat ox the
fat metabolism piece didn't add much to
the story in unfortunately in that
particular study. So, I could see a
couple uses. It does give you sustained
glucose for a long period of time. If
you're in a sport by which you cannot
feed for a long time, maybe it's useful.
Um maybe long-distance
swimming would be an example where you
could potentially use it or or sometime
when you just don't want to carry a lot
of fuel with you or maybe you're having
I don't know some type of sporting
activity where you're not able to eat a
lot. But then we thought about pre-le
feeding
and I thought I thought we were done
here but no. Can I take it before bed?
Mhm. And then run a faster morning race
without having to wake up and eat in the
middle of the night like a lot of people
who run endurance races would do. Um, so
then we designed one where we took Ukan
Superstarch right before bed. Compared
that to uh our traditional glucose
drinks were those calorie match
protocols. Yeah. Okay. So you're just
switching it out. Yeah. For what did you
switch it out for? So we would take just
regular carbohydrate or we would take
the UK superstar. What was the regular
carbohydrate? You the sucrossse. Okay.
Yeah. Um we would mix it and then one of
the things uh I was like so sugar water
or this Yeah. So calorie matched and uh
we were doing macronutrient matched
macronutrient matched and they I was
hopeful that we would see maybe like oh
you don't have to get up so early and it
was lasting so long. So the only thing
we did see which was kind of neat was
that you didn't that you did have an
increase in carbohydrate burning in the
morning which theoretically could help
with performance. It didn't translate to
it in our hands. Well it certainly
indicates there's something
physiologically happening still going on
in there. Right. You still enhance if
you were to simply ingest carbohydrate
right now. Yeah. Your right carbohydrate
burning goes up. Right. Exactly. This is
the whole premise behind why many folks
got it wrong in saying, well, these
higher fat diets or eating more fat
helps you burn more fat. Anything does.
If you eat more protein right now, you
burn more protein right now, right? You
eat more carb. But the fact that it
lasted overnight indicates that the next
morning the sugar water Yeah. wasn't
still around, but the gluc was. And in
other studies, we fed chocolate milk
before sleep and you know, different
things. And we same thing, you're still
burning a bunch of carbohydrates in the
morning.
that may be able to translate to
performance, but we just didn't we
haven't seen it yet. We haven't able to
tease that out in a running example.
Yeah. So, by default then you would have
probably lowered fat oxidation. Mhm.
Yeah. And and that's and that was
exactly what was happening. But perhaps
we didn't have something wasn't right.
Maybe the dosing was wrong because even
with protein you have to do the the
ideal dose is 40 gram which is bigger
than a lot of people are used to because
you're going so long until you're using
it again. like all night long you have
to have it. So maybe with carbohydrate
we just needed a bigger dose. One of the
things that I appreciate so much about
not only the conversation we're having
but your research line in general is
you're not only a scientist but as I
mentioned at the beginning you you've
run these races. You're an educator. You
have courses on this. In fact I think I
mentioned in the beginning that Florida
State Educator of the Year I know is on
your resume as an award. Um you're
putting these things into practice. You
have the literal textbook in the field.
you you have the you wrote the textbook
in exercise
physiology and it's so clear that when
you go after one of these studies you
don't just stop when you're on here when
you're having this conversations you're
not just saying okay this is our answer
because you know if you change one
variable maybe it changes and that why
I'm bringing this up now is you just
reminded me that as you said well maybe
we had the wrong dose maybe it was the
wrong time maybe it was the wrong
combination maybe it's the wrong person
that's a really hard skill and you rar
barely hear scientists talk like that
because they want to have a capture of
an area and they want to have clear
answers. The world wants a clear answer,
but in because you're such a
practitioner, you know, that's not
really how it works. So, I really
appreciate that about your perspective,
the way that you teach and the way you
run your lab because you're doing 10, 15
years of the same kind of study with
multiple variables changed out to
understand the real answer there. this
is not going to influence your funding.
This is not going to get you promoted or
bring more money. It's really honestly I
I'm you know jumping into your brain a
little bit here. But you're generally
trying to answer the question and you
know that there's real life there's
multiple aspects. There's just
trade-offs. There's not simple answers.
So yeah, another compliment coming your
way for your I appreciate it. Yeah, it's
it's it's great to do though. I mean,
that's the luxury of of having a
facility and a location where we can um
have the funding and the resources to to
do some of those studies. Um, and a
team, man, the team's all about it. And,
uh, I think everybody comes in knowing
kind of the the general areas we're
going to go in and and we're all in. You
know, I told you earlier, we're like,
we're trying to create this culture that
you go into a research
lab. For example, if you go into an
athletics facility, you usually see all
the all the swag and all the things. It
just feels good, right? And so, I love
that. And I want to replicate that as
best I can in research where you come
into the facility, you know, here we're
going to do great work, but it's also
going to look nice and we're going to
have things that make you want to be a
part of what we're doing. And it works.
I mean, the the students buy in, the
faculty that are present buy in, the the
research subjects want to be there
instead of just, you know, stuck in a
basement that's got no windows, you
know? It's it's just a great it's a
great spot. Yeah, man. There there's
there's love for being in the basement.
I get it. Like some of my fonder
memories had a lot of years there. Yeah.
But having dealt with that for most of
my career and now having the exact
opposite at Parker, I get it, man.
Having nice facilities and being able to
do stuff, it it changes everything.
Yeah. So, so the Yukan the superstarch
didn't do much in the what four studies
you did in that area. Three different
studies. I have personally used
resistant starches um mostly candidly. I
pretty much used Vargo for the most part
which is a slightly different thing but
similar concept here with a lot of
success in totally different
applications and totally different
scenarios than you. So I think uh
perhaps I don't know if are you going to
continue that research line or you feel
like you got that answer solved and
you're we haven't had any more pursuit
of that answer but with the product that
you're talking about I think that there
are other things that could be done in
that particular space because that's
modified to be different right that's
modified to be fast digesting uh 100%
but I don't believe all the data
and I'd love to do a study with it um
because I think it's got a lot of
potential and I know a lot of
practitioners love it. But it was the
same way with Ukan Superstar. So, um
there's something always to all these
types of studies, especially with
supplements. Like if you like it and you
think it works, then it works. Oh boy.
So, we need to stay there. However, I'd
love to do those comparison studies with
photograph because I know some of the
data were like the first 10 minutes were
extremely fast and everything stopped.
And if you look at after the 10 minutes,
then you have issues where it doesn't go
any faster. But the net was still more.
And so I I'm I'm there's just questions
I love to ask about in there. I'm sure
you have plenty of questions about that.
the uh the post extreme caloric
restriction. So weight cutting scenarios
in different sports we've used it in to
as a very fast recharge if you will as a
part it's not your first line of defense
but many different scenarios other
extreme I will just say scenarios folks
are in where fuel is going to be very
limited and unpredictable and the these
can be benefits but I would agree I
would love to see you and Vargo I guess
contact Mike and maybe you guys can come
up with some some cool stuff but more
work for sure is needed in Yeah. Yeah.
And honestly, everybody that I know who
uses it tends to like it. I just I would
love it because the studies that I've
read on the modifications, I'm just it's
not clear-cut to me. Ah, yeah. Yeah.
That's I mean, this is the beauty of how
our field works. You said this just a
few minutes ago. Clinical influences the
science. The science sometimes influence
the clinical. So, you have a lot of
clinicians and athletes and folks making
comments and great, let's bring it to
the lab. Let's see. And that's not to to
ruin it, to end it, to say it doesn't
work, but it's simply to say maybe it
doesn't do A, B, and C. Yeah. Or there's
a different use for it. Totally. Yeah.
So like these the the grants and the
funding sometimes come from these
companies and most of the time and
that's how you would get work done on
those. Um and that's a different
conversation. If we want to have it, we
can. But let's just say everything's
kosher because that's how we run the
facility.
There's a lot of things you can look at
with a different lens, like what sport
works where you have not a lot of fuel
for a long period of time. Well, maybe
there's a use. Or maybe you're the age
group athlete and you're not going to
win and you don't want insulin spiking
all the time in a race where you're out
there for a long period of time, then
maybe that's a really good product.
Yeah. You know, so there's there's
different uses, different people. You
got to really just know the individual.
Yeah, 100%. So, we went from protein, we
went to carbohydrate. Uh let's go on
actually to a little bit of a different
macronutrient-ish collagen.
I know you've done work in this area. In
fact, you were telling me earlier, I
didn't realize this, but your one study
was the longest ever study done in
collagen. Is that right? In humans,
course. Yeah. Nine months. So, there's a
lot of going on and I'll I'll actually
I'll always be honest. Um my answer has
changed on collagen probably in the last
nine to 12 months. I know I remember and
I'll save names here but people have
been talking about collagen specifically
for soft tissue injury and worked there
initially came of course out of animal
mice and urine models and other things
and I'm generally a person who says
until it's at least somewhat shown in
human I'm not going to say it doesn't
work I'm just not really going to be
concerned of it I I think it's really
important that people understand where
they are at personally on that line. So
you have kind of over on one end of the
spectrum. Unless it's been shown in five
randomized control double blind placebo
studies, I'm not taking it. Right. Okay,
fine. I personally don't live in that
world. I deal with most of the athletes
and clients are are never going to have
a randomized control trial on them
populationwise. Other folks other than
the spectrum is if there's even a
plausible cell culture study, like I'm
all in, right? Okay. I'm probably in the
middle if I'm if I would be honest. I'm
a little bit hedged more towards the
right the the the clinical trial. Let me
see it in humans at least. Ideally, not
in just like a case study
only. It's a variable I care about,
somewhat trained or whatever population
I'm looking at. So, my personal bias is
I'm there. What that means is I'm
sometimes slow, sometimes behind. people
are taking things before I would. But
I'm okay there because on aggregate I
generally win in the sense that I avoid
things not taking things. I stop doing
procedures and products where other
people have tried because I'm like well
eventually it turned out to sort of not
work for sure. So I think it's fine.
People can be wherever on the spectrum I
want. I don't think there's any issue as
long as they are either aware with
themselves or their athletes or clients
or customers where they're at on that
journey. For me collagen was on that
left end. It was very much um I don't
see much here. I don't see much here.
Plausible. Then some human studies came.
Ah I didn't see much there. It's changed
like it really has changed recently. So
much so now where I think okay I think
there is something here there and
there's enough for me to take action. So
we have integrated collagen a lot more
on this. So where are you at on that
spectrum? Tell us about you know that
study you did there what you guys
learned and in general your take. Right.
So we we began this
work six years ago and it was originally
um for the purpose of looking at dosing.
When we looked at the literature before
we began, there were um a lot in like
skin healthcare, beauty space um and
that dosing was like five to 10 grams a
day and they had like these fairly
decent outcomes over many many studies.
And so I think there was some evidence
in there, but then I was like, "All
right, I'm used to whey protein. What is
going on with this?" I'm used to like
muscle outcomes or fat metab
outcomes, body comp outcomes. Um there
are one or two papers that actually
showed that collagen had some um uh
benefit in that space, but they weren't
compared to whey weight. They were
compared to nothing. And it's usually
had a very low total protein intake and
things like that. And it's in one lab
where showing this and and that kind of
thing. So we always wondered, well,
maybe these should be not compared or we
have to look at what the outcome is. If
you're looking at muscle, I wouldn't use
collagen for muscle, right? And I think
like Stu Phillips has said that over and
over in some of his work and and it is
right. He says it a little more
aggressively than that, but okay. Yeah.
Yeah. Uh but for muscle, no, it's not
it's not where you want it. The amino
acid profile isn't there. So, we were
specifically looking at joint pain.
That's what our outcome was. And it was
in um middle-aged and older lifelong
active people. And so, it was a fun time
recruiting these individuals. Some
golfed every day, some ran every day,
but some were um elite crossfitters,
some were triathletes. So, all kinds of
a range of people, but they're all
active every single day. Uh, or not
every single day, but very active for
recruiting purposes. And then we gave
them either zero, 10, or 20 grams of
collagen per day. And it was designed as
six months. But as we were getting
closer, we said, if we're doing it this
long, let's see if we can keep them on
and do nine months. So, maybe we can
look at bone. And then we're like, well,
we probably need a year, but let's see
if we can get nine months and see what's
happening. That's right around the
number, right? Where if you see bone
mineral density changes in six months,
you probably have to be in a severe
drug protocol, damage protocol, caloric
restriction protocol or something. By
12, you'll see it. So, I only want to
flag that for people to realize if
you're looking at body composition,
muscle growth, performance, sleep,
digest, those can happen in weeks,
right? Bone takes a very long time. And
I think you nailed it. Nine months is
probably right on that tipping point.
Yeah. For most and and I I So we were
still underpowered at that point
unfortunately for bone. So we were still
primarily focused on uh it's like a
maybe we get it. Yeah. We'll see. We'll
see. And so we offered the opportunity
for the people who volunteered for six
months to stay on for three more. So
this is they're doing the six month
study and then along the way you're
going, "Hey guys, if you want to keep
going, by the way, we'll keep coaching
you. We'll keep giving you." Few months
in, we wrote to the funding agency and I
said, "I think we should extend this,
but it's going to cost X amount to do
that. Are you on board?" And so they
were on board with doing it. So we ended
up extending it. Um, and a couple
interesting things came from it. It was
mostly questionnaires in our study
because we were looking at joint pain
and we tried to use like gonometers for
range of motion and some of these other
things and we did some more high-tech
tools that we had, but they weren't
working. uh there was too much
variability in um making that happen and
also the the researcher who was doing
that was a doc student driving this work
Shalo Kiovski and she's at US now and
anyway she's still carrying on the
collagen line so that's it's carried on
in her lab now um anyway when we were
looking at this the joint pain angles we
were looking at the bottom line is over
nine months of time we had subjective
improvements in joint
pain when you were in our study. But
there were some
caveats. 10 grams did better than 20.
Interesting. 10 grams did better than
20. And if we when we dichotoized the
amount of exercise you did, it was most
helpful if you exercised for greater
than 180 minutes per week of exercise.
So with that said, it in our hands that
was our outcome. 10 grams per day was
the dose. Nine months was the timeline.
We saw improvements in joint pain that
were significant and you had to exercise
more than 180 minutes to feel those
benefits. The cool relationship that we
were maybe should have expected but
didn't is they did some uh mood state
assessments and such and those people
who had better knee pain actually had
better improvements in mood as you would
expect, not in so much pain. Um so yeah,
that that changed my my tune on it
because I was unsure of it entirely. Um,
and then what we didn't measure, we you
always wish you had a better
questionnaire or something and people
just talking to you after these studies
and they're like changed my life. Some
of them, not all of them, but some of
them were like this was amazing. I and I
noticed that I came off of it for three
months. Thing is, it takes a while. It's
one of those things you have to take and
then they we started seeing differences
around six months and then they were
sustained around nine months. So, it
took quite a while. Um, but it's enough
that as a middle-aged athlete, uh, I've
started implementing, uh, 10 grams a
day. And we don't, in our study, we
didn't even mix it with vitamin C, which
is probably which is the recommended
way. Yeah. Like all Keith Bar's work,
you know, is fascinating. And they're
they're the best at it. we were kind of
late to the game and just wanted to have
these joint pain outcomes specifically
because there were evidence of it even
in um young athletes like college
athletes y of fixing joint pain and they
didn't even have joint pain to begin
with our people all had joint pain but
no diagnosed osteoarthritis
and we still we saw these benefits but
even in young people it was shown so I
think the benefit is there I would take
it separately from whey I would use way
for my muscle building efforts I would
use collagen for my joint pain okay
handful of follow-ups on you there. Uh,
number one, for anyone at home, collagen
can be got very cheaply. So, in fact, I
think Keith's initial stuff was just 50
cents at the store gelatin. Um, so you
can look up I'm sure we can probably put
some stuff in the show notes, but you
you can literally make this stuff for
very cheap. If you want, you can, of
course, get it from a supplement
company. Most of them, I know the
Momentous one is already made with
vitamin C. 50 milligrams is the general
dosage I think for the activation. The
reason for that in case you're wondering
is a lot of the quick way to explain
this is the collagen needs to be
actually absorbed and utilized and
vitamin C is an important co-actor in
that process. So, I skipped a bunch of
science and that's not totally correct
what I said, but that for the most part,
if you're wondering like why the heck
did he say vitamin C if that felt out of
random for you? Perhaps we can talk at a
separate time about that, but that's
that's why you bring it up. And again,
the collagen shots and other stuff from
Momentous is already in there. But most
other companies, if you have a different
place that you like to get your
supplements from, a lot of them are
mixing it with the vitamin C for that
exact reason.
So, I wanted to make sure we did that so
I didn't forget because people are gonna
ask, "Okay, where the heck do I get this
stuff from?" Yeah. And how do I get it
there? But back to your study design
question. Did you do serial design or
serial testing or was it simply the six
month ninemonth mark that you did it? In
other words, they came in a lot. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. We were seeing them
regularly month monthly. So, you had
your And what all measures did you have
there besides the joint pain things like
that? the cognitive surveys and we at
the time we were we were doing body comp
outcomes as well obviously with the DEXA
and the bone and then we also had um um
the actual like gonometer measures but
we had to basically throw it all away
because it was just useless at the end
unfortunately. Yeah. So you saw
virtually no change until about the
six-month mark and that was your first
point of statistical difference was at
that mark. Yeah. Not that clean but
roughly. Yeah. Um and it held on for the
nine months. Yes. And again, in the
people that exercise the most. Yeah. So,
yeah. Do I think it's the next thing? I
don't know. It just seems to sway me a
little bit that if joint pain's a
problem for you, it'd be worth
considering because it isn't that
expensive. It's very easy to take. Um,
and it's it's worth trying before you go
and have surgery or something, you might
as well give it a go. Well, what are the
known downsides besides cost?
Yeah. Nothing. Yeah. Yeah. It's not
going to help build your muscle. It
won't help. Sure. But for a pretty
reasonable I don't know what I don't
know probably $40 a month like maybe at
the most. Yeah, something like that. Um,
relative to the pain you're
experiencing, if it even has a 10 or 15%
reduction in pain. Do you remember what
the magnitude of effect was on the pain?
Was it something like that? That's a
good question. I don't remember. I would
imagine it's not this insane
life-changing my arthritis is gone my
entire life, but it's probably more of
like a I went from a seven out of 10 to
five out of 10. Yeah, the mean the mean
was a significant increase, but it
wasn't mind-blowing. But you had those
one-offs that were like, "My goodness,
that's that's pretty cool to listen to."
And, you know, that's not it just drives
more questions. You know, now we want to
see what else could we do. We took a ton
of blood and we're still analyzing it.
So, we're trying to figure out some
mechanisms behind it with some of the
like osteoplastic or osteoclastic
activity, some of the things around
collagen um synthesis and degradation.
And so, um Shaloa now is working on
those outcomes from from that sample.
And then there's other things we're
working on too and and had some momentum
for potentially use in recovery from
surgery like ACL repairs and there I
think some work needs to be done in that
space. We have a real good relationship
with now with orthopedic medicine where
I am and then Shalo works in a
department that has that focus. So I
think she'll be heading up a lot of
those studies and be worth watching her
her uh profile grow here in the next
couple years on that topic. Okay. So we
can assume very low
downside likely plausible mild benefit.
If that meets the criteria for you to
take action, great. If it doesn't,
that's fine, too. Right. All I'm
assuming you want to do is just make
sure people know what is possibly
happening and then it's up for them to
decide if that meets their action
criteria. Yeah. No doubt about it. And I
I I do think based on the data we have,
if you're not exercising a lot, don't do
it. Like if you have knee pain and
you're not active, I wouldn't do it.
Last two questions on that one. Why do
you think the ones that exercise the
most are the only ones or the ones that
saw the most benefit?
The probably the most likely answer is
blood flow. You get blood flow to the
area to areas that are hard to get blood
flow to. Um the other thing we didn't do
was time like purposely tell them when
to take it in the day before exercise.
Whereas like Keith's work that shows a
massive benefit matters is when you take
it before exercise um so that you have
it in there when you're gonna get blood
flow going. We just split it morning and
night so that we could do 00 55 510 1010
through the day. So those are some
things that we could have done better.
So you need to repeat that study and
specifically give it to them in that 45
to 90 minutes pre-workout window which
is where most it probably would be
better to do a possibly because a bigger
effect. Sure. And if we did like a
training study where we actually
controlled the exercise to get them to
the minutes we need and then all these
other factors. But I tell you a nine
month study the way we did it which is
pretty free living still took four
years. Um and so if we redid it with all
those other variables. How do I miss the
math there? That's science right? It is.
I mean you can't enroll everybody at
once. So you trickle them in and roll
them in. And because of that it takes
years. Yeah. Yeah. But you mentioned
it's free living. that's going to have
the most ecological validity, the most
external validity, right? That what that
means is that's the most realistic to a
real life scenario where someone just
they're taking a scoop of it. They're
not doing it the the best way. They're
not having a perfectly designed training
protocol. And you still see in my
opinion as a we'll just say fairly
well-trained scientists at this point in
my career, that's actually really
powerful because you didn't do it at the
right time. you didn't control for those
things and you still saw a statistically
significant albeit mild benefit. I think
most people listening would say I will
take a mild reduction in my daily pain.
Yeah. Yeah. And and obviously for a 50
calorie Yeah. And the cognitive side
like that's what was nice is like the
the sca the scale the scales and
subscales were all showing you know if
you had the improvement in pain you
started feeling better in all these
other areas of your life. So, the last
question I have for you on that
particular study was, and I know
everyone listening has been waiting for
me to ask this or hoping I would, how
did 10 work better than 20? Yeah, I'm
not going to have a great answer for
you. Yeah, we we don't really know. Um,
it didn't make sense to us and it's one
of those Why did you even think to do 10
versus rooms? So, a lot of times the
dose on a prepackage is 15.
And when we were looking at those data,
there wasn't a lot in the
space. Um, and then we were talking with
some of the companies that produce it,
some were saying that 20 was what they
sell, but I'd seen efficacy at 10. And I
thought, well, we should probably figure
out what dose we should be taking. Um,
and so that's why we designed it that
way. Uh, but I don't know, maybe 15
would have been the best if we didn't do
it. 0, 10, and 20. And 20 did some
things, but the 10 just had kind of the
most overall benefit. So that's what I
would recommend at this point. Right.
It's interesting because rarely with
protein and albeit collagen is not the
same thing as whey
protein. I just can't think of too many
situations in which when you go more
than you had a lesser effect. It's
almost always the more protein or
protein like the more amino acids, the
more anything in this space, either you
get a benefit or you at worst get
a maybe not a greater increase in
benefit relative to the greater increase
in in substrate or volume or food or
calories, but in this case, you actually
see a dampered effect. Yeah. And I'll
tell you like that's we've been
struggling with that for a while. And
how do we interpret that? And um you
know, the reviewers had the same
comments. is like I don't I'm sure that
was comment number one. Yeah, I don't
get it. So, you know, that that
particular paper tries to outline some
of the potential reasons, but in
reality, we don't really know what
happened. Struggling to answer a few
questions. Yeah. So, we're we're we're
not sure. Um I think that's
honestly no, and I don't mean this I
know you won't take it this way, but
it's also very plausible it's artifact.
No doubt. As in it might not be a real
genuine finding.
you weird things can happen, right? And
this is why another thing you said
earlier as a passing comment that I want
to pull out is another great sign of a
phenomenal scientist. You mentioned a
study coming from one lab before and you
say, "Okay, you would say the same thing
I know you would about your lab." Oh,
for sure. So, don't over interpret this
ninemon study. Right. Right. It's like,
well, let's see another lab repeat it.
Let's do a different circumstance.
Without a doubt. Without a doubt. Yeah.
I mean that's the whole deal is what's
so exciting about the field of
performance nutrition in general for me
it's not a dead science it evolves
constantly and that's what's great is
like stuff I taught five years ago is
probably changing the way I teach it
today and could change in another five
years and so you know taking as a whole
that like keeps us very interested and
motivated uh uh all the time. Okay.
Well, for the record I'm going to keep
taking 20. I don't care what your data
say. I'm not kidding. I'm not stopping
it at all. It's it's too much of a
potential win. But um I I'll be honest,
one of the major reasons I changed my
position in this field was your paper.
Once I saw your name, that kind of a
study on I was like, okay, now I can
start believing this data because it's
not against the other scientists who
were publishing earlier than you, but
it's just the fact that I now saw it on
multiple labs, a lab I recognized and
the data were believable. And what I
mean by that is when you do real world
studies, you rarely see everything works
every time, right? It's like, well,
maybe joint pain went down, but they
slept worse or this marker in the blood
went up and this other marker went up,
but then this one didn't. We And anytime
I see a paper where like everything gets
better, right? I'm always like, "No."
Yeah. We don't we don't suffer from that
problem.
Awesome.
We've
hit protein and carbohydrates and we
went to collagen. I think actually would
be helpful and I sorry I forgot this but
maybe let's take a real quick step
backwards. What the heck is collagen?
We heard about it a lot. We talk about
it. We've sort of been kind of saying
that almost as interchange with protein.
It's not. But can you just give people a
quick understanding of what collagen
actually is? Sure. Yeah. I mean you
could you think of it as a protein. It's
just got sort of different amino acids
that make up its structure than you
would a whey protein. So, it's all kinds
of amino acids linked together. But the
biggest sort of magic to it, at least in
the literature, is that it's um very
high in proline. Yeah. And glycine. And
if you can get these cyclic proline
molecules,
hydroxyprolines out of the structure,
that's what makes it different. Um the
the whey protein for example is very
high in leucine whereas this is
basically absent of leucine and and and
so that there that's why it's not a
complete protein. It's kind of thought
of for years like the rubbish sort of
protein. Don't even use it. Throw it
away. Um but lucine is the amino acid
that's the primary driver. Well, it's a
large driver of muscle growth. Hence
your comments earlier about whey protein
being Hey, thanks Stu Phillips. Great.
That's the one for muscle growth. This
one is basically absent of it. Yeah. And
so it's the throwaway protein. Right.
Right. And and u Yeah. So collagen in
itself would be higher in these proline
hydroxyproline sort of
linkages. It's thought I mean there's
data in animals showing that um as large
of a
nonopeptides nine amino acids are
getting through intact.
That hasn't been shown in other places.
Normally they all get all the proteins
will be sort of broken apart into
individual amino acids then brought in.
These are coming in and regularly in two
to three amino acid structures and then
the largest I've seen is nine. And then
they're then these certain patterns that
are that supposedly are are what can
help to drive that to um uh be a part of
the matrix for like tendons and
ligaments and uh that that the
structural components that it's supposed
to be used for. Let me make sure I
understood that correctly. If you were
to ingest majority of different types of
proteins, you're going to have them go
into your gut as that piece of steak,
that that milk, that yogurt, that
whatever you're getting it from. The
great, it's going to be in your stomach
as a whole protein. By the time it gets
into your blood, it is now in the blood
not as the whole protein anymore, but as
its individual amino acid components.
Right? So, this is what your gut and
your digestive tract are doing is
they're breaking it down from the total
protein into the amino acids. But what
you're saying is what's unique about
collagen is it's not necessarily broken
down the entire way. Yeah. And I'm
skeptical of it. I mean, I've read all
I've I've read all the literature on it.
We didn't measure the the tripeptides
and the bigger molecules coming through,
although we had plans to. It kind of
fell through, unfortunately. Technical
stuff, I'm sure. Yeah. Yeah.
Um, but that is what they're the the
literature base is saying that that is
what makes it novel and unique. So,
yeah. So, in your blood, you could pull
it out and you'll see two or three of
these amino acids still linked together,
which would be insanely uncommon. If you
were to, for example, put a an IV line
in me and you measured my blood and I
had a meal, you could see how many how
much protein I ate, but you would have
no idea what I actually ate. In this
case, it'd be different. you would in
theory, if this holds true, be able to
say, "Wow, you specifically ate
collagen." Right? And I think the where
the where the breakdown is, this is very
weird scientifically, by the way, if
you're like, "What are these guys
learning about?" Like, I'm fixated on
this because this is really really odd.
It it is. And and it's it it should make
you a bit skeptical about it because
some of the some of the companies
unfortunately are saying if you take
this type then, for example, like type
one collagen, it would go straight to
tissues that need type 1 collagen. I've
never seen that. I don't think that's
actually the case. Um to me it seems
like those particular tissues are made
up of certain types of amino acid
chains. This particular type of protein
has an abundance of those. Y um and then
if you can get it into the blood and
then driven to the tissue that needs it
perhaps you'd see a benefit. There's a
lot of ifs ands or buts in that
statement. Sure. Okay. So leucine is the
one in a in uh most proteins that drives
muscle protein synthesis. Over here
we're not talking about leucine. Um,
we're talking about a couple of other
ones. Remind us of what those other ones
are and quickly why they matter. Yeah.
The components of of collagen
specifically that make it more unique
because of their pattern is really that
the the serene glycine and and proline
and the those repeating structures
create these like helical structures
that can actually potentially do good
for you. Got Okay, great. So, um, I want
to focus a little bit more on one of
those amino acids because I know you've
done some work tangentially. I'm I'm
transitioning here. I'm I'm bridging a
gap a little bit here and that is
glycine. So you don't need to give me
the structural details here but we know
why leucine matters. Why does glycine
matter? What does it do? And then we'll
get into some of your supplementation
work here. Yeah. So the the context by
which we used glycine was uh with a
product called betane.
Betane also known as trimethlycine.
trimethoglycine or also known as betane.
Betine bane. I've seen people
mispronounce this. There's a thousand
different ways. Spelled uh b a t. B t a
i n e. Yeah, there you go. B T A. So
what the way we got started with betane
was we were um I had a student named
Brandon Willingham who was interested in
heat and thermore regulation. And so we
were designing some studies for him to
try to tease out some potential
nutritional ways to affect hydration,
thermmorreulation and um I was aware of
betane a little bit ba mostly based from
animal model research that I had seen.
So I shared those with Brandon and said,
you know, start diving into all this.
And um he did a brilliant job in sort of
coming up with various mechanisms by
which betane may be useful. And so the
literature on betane was quite
fascinating to me because I don't
typically read about sheep and cows and
pigs. Um but they were these are that's
a standard product that's in the feed or
the water supply of animals in hot human
conditions that need to survive. And
there were data showing improved
mortality in these animals that have
betane supplementation. And then and
this is probably by the way 10 years.
Oh, more than that. Okay. Yeah. Because
I know it's been on the in our field
published for it's fairly recent I guess
is what in our field 10. Yeah. Yeah. Is
Yeah. But the animal research was older
and uh so Brandon led a review paper
that our group put out and just kind of
describing why we think this might work
and all this and then he designed a
really nice study that uh unfortunately
covid times hit and he was unable to do
it. So we had to um design it where we
didn't do any exercise. And so here's
the thing. It when the betane was in the
product of the animals that had good
outcomes in in the heat and
survival, the way it had been used in
the one therm paper that was out there
was an acute dose. And so that was a
mismatch to me. And so we said, well,
why don't we try to load it just like
you would creatine. So if I take this
right before my heat exposure, yeah,
potentially nothing. Probably not going
to do anything. in that in the one study
that existed, it it didn't show
anything. Um, and and so I reached out
to the authors of that paper and I was
just gussing in with Doug Casa. We're
trying to figure out kind of what went
wrong, what went right, and and everyone
basically dismissed it because it didn't
do anything out of a really good lab.
Um, and so we said, well, let's look at
a little bit different. Let's try to
load this. So we ended up giving it in
the first study for just a week uh of
loading. And then we had to do passive
heat exposure, which means you don't
exercise or do anything. You just sit in
a hot environment which is 40° C in our
in our um thermon chamber. Okay. So you
got participants sitting in there. Yeah.
They're just sitting in a chair in the
heat at 40°. At 40° C that's cooking.
Yeah. It's hot. It's hot, but it's not
enough of a stress. Yeah. And so in that
study, not surprisingly, we didn't show
any benefits to doing passive heat
exposure. So if you live in a hot
environment, this isn't going to do
anything for you. You need to start
doing some work in that environment.
So then we were able to finally do the
study that we had intended to after we
got through with the COVID restrictions
and we started doing cycling in the heat
and so same design again we decided to
go ahead and uh load it for a week and
then we did um 70% V2 max in the chamber
and we turned the temperature to 33
degrees Celsius so that we could keep
core temperature in a range that
wouldn't eliminate us or make us end the
study early. Um, and we actually found
some really cool results in that
particular study. We're we're writing
the study up now for publication, so
it's it's not out yet. So, you can't
tell us the results of that. You can
tell us that it was pretty cool, though.
It was It was pretty cool, and it was
enough to drive another study. And and
and then in the last one, we were
designed this study to be specifically
in firefighters who are um prone to all
kinds of heat issues, obviously. And uh
again, we're we're we wrap that study
up. We're trying to publish that one
sort of simultaneous here. And so in the
next hopefully 6 months or so, we'll
have both of these out and uh another
direction for people to start looking at
this particular product for heat
thermal. I won't ask you about the
results. That's faux pa, right? You
can't tell us that until it comes out.
But I I can ask you some things about
dosages and things like that. Before we
do that, you were telling me earlier
about a little bit of the protocol for
the firefighter overheating. So, that
was not sit easy at 40 degrees. No.
Yeah, that was this was live. And so,
yeah, my whole study team was they were
phenomenal. They all went to the fire
training grounds that are near to us.
Um, and they were able to convince the
fire chief and everybody to get on board
and they they have a a conx box, like
basically a large cargo unit that
shipping container. Yeah. That they
light on fire. They put bales of hay in
there and they light the thing on fire
and that's uh sometimes that's training
in there, sometimes it's not. So, we
were able to do um a stair climb up and
down several times and then go kneel in
the conx block that's that's on fire.
And then we had uh temperature gauges on
the roof and on the on the floor. So,
they were kneeling but the floor temp
which like was outrageous. It was it was
cooking and even on the bottom where
they were kneeling it was like being in
an oven, you know, 500 600 degrees. It
was 4,000 degrees on top. The ceiling.
Yeah, the ceiling height. So, gets a
little bit gnarly. Uh just a touch. And
they no longer impressed by your 200
degree sauna, by the way. So, they kneel
in there. They had to kneel in there for
15 minutes. And even in just that amount
of time, I mean, um you're talking about
20 minutes losing a liter, liter of
water. Yeah. Easy. I believe that you
get that hot, two, three pounds. Yeah.
Going to be gone. So
you the the results will be what the
results will be but what you were
looking at in case this hasn't been
clear yet is is that supplement helping
them manage the heat better. Right.
Right. So the supplement had data which
is why we went that direction to
um uh basically help as an osmolate and
as a cellular hydration factor. So water
follows it. It's in the cell and perhaps
it's keeps your cell hydrated longer. It
also has some properties that are
published in other studies that show
that it might protect proteins from
degrading in hot temperatures. Yeah.
Yeah. So the com the combination of
those two things um the increases in
cellular volume perhaps plasma volume
were intriguing enough for us to sort of
go down this path for the last six
years. So how much what's the dosage?
The original doses we were doing were 50
milligrams per kilogram body weight.
that we did it a relative. Um and then
by the time we started the firefighter
study, the the doc student who ran that
um Lily Rea, she um kind of looked
through everything that was relevant at
that point and we decided to give a
standard three grams um for everybody,
not based on not based on body weight
for the firefighter study. Yeah. Okay.
So, three grams per day. You mentioned
really quickly there a couple of ways of
how it could theoretically work. I know
that this is early in the field. It's 10
years old at best. you got some
publications you're working on. Surely
others are, but outside of handling heat
stress more effectively. Can you think
of any other known or plausible benefits
of it as a supplement? I mean, in our
work, we were strictly looking at it for
these. I know other people put it in as
a hydration factor in various drinks.
So, like pre-workouts and such. It's if
you look at available in many many
supplements. Yeah, it's already in many
different things. In fact, um, some of
the products we were looking at, we had
to find in a way that we could just get
the raw ingredient because it's just
it's a mixed in everything. But yeah,
it's usually in there. Sometimes it's
like a filler. Honestly, that's what it
was used for. Um, and and uh cheap the
cheap. Yeah. And it looks like a new
nice shiny word to have on your label.
Mh. Uh but I think it is possible that
using it in this manner um could be
helpful for those who are doing things
in extreme heat, right? Uh what I'm
curious about is is if it goes beyond
these extreme extreme examples and maybe
it would help even like migrant field
workers, for example, and people who are
doing labor in hot environments and we
just we're just not there yet. Yeah. So
in theory, if it could keep your core
temperature lower, but enables you to
have a higher sweat rate, there's lots
of applications or at least maintain
your sweat rate, you wonder if it has
plausible benefit for endurance folks.
Not even extreme stuff, the ultra stuff,
which could be the case, but even a
soccer game in the heat. um a baseball
game probably not as much, but any real
outdoor activity from a sporting
perspective where you're going to be in
a lot of heat, I don't know if there's
any data on that, but it's plausible.
Yeah, I think that's where we're going.
I mean, so we've done doing nothing to
doing cycling to doing some things in a
real applied setting with tactical
athletes, these firefighters. Um and if
that story holds true as I I think it
might then I think we can go at the next
phase where it will be probably two
aims. One would be like FEMA kind of
work. Oh sure. And then I think another
one could be like the MI migrant
fieldworker side and then I think we
have a whole slew of work to do in
athletics. Wow. Awesome. That's a super
interesting one. I have RSS alerts on my
PubMed for that. I'm like looking for
something to come out in that area. So,
I know I'll see your firefighter study
the day that it hits there. Maybe you
can send me a reminder text, but I'll
read it. No. Either way, man. Let's go
from that to a another similar sounding
supplement that has that you've done
some work in that people again now lots
of stuff out there, but people haven't
heard about it. Um, and that's taken or
theocrine. Um, so tell us about that,
what what you've done in there, and
maybe even just start us off by telling
us what heck it even is. Yeah. So, we
got interested in that um teocrine
uh which is sort of the branded name of
theocrine, right? So, spelled by the way
here it's like one H versus the not Yes.
H in there basically. Very similar like
t like te e a. Yeah. C r i n e tine.
Uh so a long long time ago I did some
work in caffeine. Yep. And ephedrin when
you could do it. Oh man, the days. Yeah.
This was the late 90s. and and we were
uh we were doing these different studies
of metabolism and performance with these
things. And so caffeine was always sort
of an interest of mine and then
tacocrine came up as uh a possible
caffeine mimedic that may not have some
of the known side effects of caffeine.
So can I take it and get the benefits
but not have the crash the jitter? Yeah,
they said the jitter specifically was
sort of how it's how it's marketed. And
so we said well let's take a look
because it was a product that we were
interested. I had another student who
Man, if you're making supplements, you
got to be you got to block Mike. You can
tell he's on the hunt here. Yeah, it's
funny. We're uh we don't mean to. We're
just trying to do what we can to put
good work out there. Uh but this
particular one was interesting. We
looked at um caffeine at uh 300
milligrams. Um tin known effective dose.
Yeah, not crazy high, but not crazy
high. And then we did tear at 300. So,
we were matching them. And then we did a
combo where we did 150 and 150 of each
and a placebo. So there were four arms
to it. Yeah.
Um in our hands that people were well
rested. They came in, they took the
supplement, they waited 90 minutes, and
then they did a whole bunch of tests,
1RM, they did some rowing, they did all
kinds of different physiological, you
know, battery of tests that they that we
were running them through. Um, and when
we did this, the uh the most effective
one we had of all of those was straight
caffeine. It beat tacocrine at 300. It
beat the combo. It beat the placebo. Um,
and the outcomes were specifically for
perceived um, uh, energy that they had
for the event. It didn't actually change
the weight they moved or their time in
anything, but they felt better doing it.
They had more focus and motivation to
exercise with that dose. Now, I think
where I've seen the literature go, and
we didn't do this work, was more in
recovering from perhaps like sleep
deprivation or cases where you're super
run down and then tasks that are more uh
cognitive in nature like
marksmanship, vigilance, you know, some
cognitive skills. Um, that's where I've
seen this be shown more effective than
the way that we designed it. Yeah. So
what you'd see in general with caffeine
is you have a cognitive benefit right
people are aware of that alert focused
so on and so forth but there's a several
decades of research on the physical
performance benefit so in general
endurance performance is enhanced and
things like that with teocrine you saw
many of the cognitive stuff as you
mentioned but the physical stuff I
actually I don't think I've seen a
single paper that's shown a physical
benefit yet maybe I've missed some
none are there. So, I've used it
personally. Um, I don't I'm not a huge
personal fan of caffeine, so teocrine
was appealing in that sense. I don't
really like stimulants in general, but
me like I didn't have a huge thing
there. I have friends
though, love it, completely love it.
they've gone completely off caffeine and
are pure tea cream and I know other
folks have put it in a mix in
combination maybe 50 migs of caffeine
and 150 of tea cream or something like
that. Um my answer to them is always
like if you feel great for those ones if
you're per amazing I just don't
anticipate too much performance benefit
from it. Not exactly sure why. I don't
know if you have any thoughts on why
caffeine does it but tea cream doesn't.
Well, caffeine's always the
sledgehammer. Yeah. Right. You see all
these products and it's touting this or
that in it, but then you just look at
the caffeine dose because that's driving
the response that you're probably
feeling. I learned mix of caffeine.
Yeah. As you're feeling from it. So, I
don't I'm not I'm not sure about about
that. In our hands, I think perhaps we
we could adjust the dosages and maybe
try something different, but man, 300 is
pretty common dose. So, yeah. And you
start getting past that, you start
getting in the negative. Like there's a
down slope with too much caffeine with
performance. Yeah. And I don't know
about, you know, now now that we
understand like genetic responders to it
and stuff, maybe there's something like
that for teocrine as well. I don't know.
Yeah. We'll see. Okay. So, we handed a
couple of those ones. Um I would love to
get I was hoping we get the chance to
talk about some of the vascular work
you've done in creatine, but maybe we'll
save that for another day. Is there
maybe you get done a couple of papers or
you've worked on some papers in that
area, right? Can you give us a quick
maybe response to that? So once again
looking at how uh clinical and sport
performance nutrition cross over
creatine is a really good example of
that. Um we have some experts at FSU in
vascular health and um blood flow
dynamics and microvasculare
and so we were actually trying to put
creatine through microalysis probes and
see if we could get it directly to the
tissue we want because you can put those
in muscle as well. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
That's how I'm familiar with for the
most part. Yeah. So, so there were some
interesting things we were thinking
through and so uh PhD student that was
in the program, Holly Clark, she wrote a
nice review on the possibilities of it
for vascular health. So, it's not the
actual study. Her dissertation was and
that's not published yet, but um the the
paper she wrote was all all review.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, that one again is
hopefully hopefully that one will be out
here. I had heard word on the street you
were working on some vascular stuff with
creatine. So, I was hoping to pull that
out of you, but okay. We'll have to use
the review and the plausible mechanisms.
I would be surprised if we don't see
positive benefits there. Maybe not in
your study because the study design or
maybe it does it doesn't but having gone
to that paper. Uh and that's open access
paper. Yeah. Yeah. Anyone can go read
that if you want. Um I would I would
struggle I think you guys are not not on
to something there. So oftent times we
talk about creatine. I've been as
staunch of a supporter as possible for
the well-rounded benefits of creatine,
but rarely have I seen people talk about
the vascular benefits of that. Yeah.
More, you know, with creatine, it's
funny, it's pretty ubiquitous now, but
it's like it's helping with so many
different realms. And I think you would
probably have a lot of folks say they
don't even take it for performance
anymore. Really, it's just a good side
effect by percentage. More people are
taking it for non-performance-based
things. It's just really cool. I mean, I
think it's fascinating how it's going. I
love seeing all the updates in that
space and brain health and all these
other benefits of it. Isn't it wild,
man? When we were kids, people were
having protein shakes before bed and
taking creatine. And now, 30 years
later, now we know you should. We're
right back here. They all see meattheads
run the world, friends. It's not It's
only bro science until it's real
science. Okay. Um, the reason I'm going
to cut you short on that one, I know you
have more to say on that is is I
actually want to get to one more smaller
quicker question and then one more uh a
couple more areas I think of interest.
People are aware of
prebiotics, but what are post biotics?
You have these gut microbes that you can
either feed with fuel or you can take
what they produce, which would be a
postbiotic. Ah, so you have a prebiotic
to feed them and then you have a
postbiotic which is what they're
producing and a probiotic would be
right. You have the actual food form of
it. There you go. Yeah. So you have
pre-post and uh your mid here. So yeah,
what do we know about the postbiotics?
Yeah. So in our space, we're using this
um to look at again gut health,
something that's being produced. Um the
biggest one to date that we kind of know
a lot about is um like butyrate. You
know, that's one that's really common as
a postbiotic.
Um it's one of the ones we have the most
generation of naturally, but it's also
one that can be go ary with different
food issues, gut upset, different issues
that could happen. And so we are right
now one of my doctoral students is um
going to be looking at a postbiotic that
contains a butyrate and then we're going
to look at gut health. We're looking at
stool samples in this one in a
collaboration with this um great gut
microbiome physiologist Robbie Nagpaul
who works with us. Yeah. Robbie lab in
your lab or institute, right? Yep. And
so Robbie is going to help us with all
of that. And then we're going to be
exercising in the heat for people who
are unaccustomed to both exercise and
exercise in the heat to try to disrupt
the gut to see if we can do it. Um, and
then there are some papers showing a a
link between butyrate and sleep. And so
we're going to see if there's any
residual changes that are occurring in
sleep. Um, and we're going to do it as a
time course so that we can uh take the
supplement and then see when it shows up
in the stool sample so that we know it's
actually getting in there, which is a
step that is uh easy to skip because
it's harder to do and it's expensive,
but we're going to make sure it's
actually getting to where we want it to
be getting. Um, so if that doesn't work,
then the part two of the study is a
little bit disrupted. But assuming it
gets where it's going to go and we'll
have those answers, then we're going to
look at um a little bit of performance
just cuz I don't I always check
performance, but uh mostly gut health
and then some of the sleep dynamics.
Okay. Now, uh we should talk about that
specifically. I we we can do some fun
things in that area, too. But have you
thought at all yet, and you may not,
that's okay. And you may not actually
know it offhand about how you're going
to be delivering that and the dosage of
your postbiotic. I don't know if you
guys got to those details yet with your
study design. Yeah, we do. And I'm or
maybe your grad student probably. Yeah,
I don't remember the exact dosage that
we're that we're using in that one.
Okay. I'm sure you guys get that figured
out there. There'll be another case
though of you may have to tinker with a
few types and styles and delivery
formats and things like that. So, you
got another 15 years or so for that one,
right? Got too many lanes going. Yeah.
No, I get it, man. That's pretty
awesome. the company that that produces
that product that we are asking for a
grant from. It's actually already a
product on the market. It's called Core
Biome. Okay. Yeah. So, that's the one
we're going to be using. So, I don't
remember the dose, but that's the
product. Core Biome. Mhm. Okay. Well,
we'll see whether or not it works. Yeah.
So, maybe we'll start taking it, maybe
we won't. We know with your lab it's a
50-50 shot. No doubt. No doubt. Okay. I
want to give one more area here and
we're staying in the lane of sports
performance but a paper that you
published also I'm pretty sure is open
access that your group was a part of
rather um supplementation for muscle
damage and recovery in females. Mhm. I
get this
non-stop, but tell me what you guys
found in that and what do we know? What
can we do for th that population about
supplements for and actually was
specifically post exercise muscle damage
was for the most part in that paper.
Yeah. So those were stemming from a
series of uh muscle damage studies we
were running some in our lab somewhere
in collaboration with other uh
universities. Um that particular one was
with Anna Mun who was in South Africa
and now he's in Australia. Um but we
were we had finished a male version of
that paper in that study. I see how this
went. Yes. And we wanted to um get more
data. As you know, females in all
research but sports research are
severely
underrepresented and uh we're doing our
best to to move into that space as best
we can as um strategically as we can so
that we get good data to come out of
what we're looking at. Um and and so
that was sort of a start years ago. That
paper is probably 10 years old now where
we're going in and trying to get um just
pull any data we could from data that
had female athletes and did any kind of
muscle damage structure uh in their
design. Um and it turns out in that
particular paper there wasn't all that
much that was different. It was proper
calories, proper energy, proper
carbohydrates, proper protein as well.
So we were looking at sort of were there
anything different? Then we started
looking at things like creatin and you
know what else might be in the mix. The
the unique part about that paper is we
just designed it to look at every study
that had women to date y in a damaged
study. So that was that was what was
unique about that and in our hands um we
followed that with a couple of papers
where we ran downhill at 10 or 15%
depending on the study um just to induce
damage and then we did that in men and
women and we were trying to see uh if we
could use some of these multi-ingredient
performance supplements to fix anything
and did any of them work? No.
Ow. Uh, without ruining another
supplement company's uh life there, what
kind of multi-ingredients do you
remember off hand? The type of things
that were in these or were these kind of
creatine, beta alanine, protein
combination things that mean? Yeah,
exactly. Yeah, it was taking all the
ones that you know work individually and
then you put them all together. And when
I say no, I was being a little
physicious. Like the individual products
will do something, but we're not just
not seeing a robust enough response to
say you're going to mitigate this. Yeah.
You might like come back to normal a
tad better. I don't even want to say
faster. Yeah. Um we were misqued one
time was someone pulled open a when we
used to read magazines and like pull
open a magazine and said, "You're in
there. It says uh you recovered like
300% faster." I'm like, "We didn't even
measure faster." like it wasn't even
part of the design.
Oh gosh. Yeah. Well, if you think the
misquing was u happening before, just
wait right after this comes out. Just
wait. Anything we do know of that will
enhance recovery, maybe it was not from
your paper or your research, but I'm I'm
actually most interested in knowing if
there are things that are specifically
more effective for females that we know
of, or is that not the case? Yeah, not
yet. Not yet that I'm aware of. There's
no reason to think females need to do
anything different from a nutrition or
supplementation perspective. Not at this
point. But I'll tell you
like it's really hard to distinguish
because you look at the research in
females and female athletes particularly
particularly around like menstrual cycle
changes and throughout um the life span
as well and there's definitely things
that could help with different life
phases. Mhm. Um, and then there's some
data that show like performance isn't
really changed in the research that
exists around the cycle at least to
date. But there's clearly a bunch of
side effects or physiological effects
that the women feel and all the
literature on exist that could make you
not want to perform, not want to go
exercise. Um, and I don't I think that's
sort of being discounted a little bit in
what I'm reading so far. So, I don't
know. Uh there's a lot more work that
has to be done there. If you look at it
as black and white on a piece of paper,
I don't think you can pinpoint one
thing, but I'm sure there are things
that work for certain individuals and
certain women that have a way to
strategize their their nutrition. So, as
a general answer, probably not. At the
specific level, though, there may be. We
just don't have those data yet. Yeah, I
would even say there there probably is.
I just we just need more work in that
area. Amazing. you've been super
generous with your time, but I'm not
letting you off the hook before I get
one more thing out of you. You you were
telling me about um some upcoming
studies you've got going on. And you
mentioned the travel one. I don't know
if you can talk about that, but is there
any other cool stuff you got going on?
Yeah, so uh one of our doc students, um
Tim Gre is much more straight sport
performance, sports science. Um he
spends an inordinate amount of time
working with FSU athletics in different
spaces now um about halfime in in there
and halftime with us. Um but he's
interested in travel and the effects on
sleep and also on performance. And so
he's going to um be able to travel with
one of our women's teams in the spring
and take three different trips with the
team um to so we're in Florida. So, an
east coast trip and then he'll also do
two west coast trips all the way out
here to California. And so, he'll do one
where they stay on uh east coast time
and then one where they switch to west
coast time. Um, and so then he'll make
he'll have uh force plates he's bringing
with him. So, have force place data,
hand grip data, and then all the sleep
metrics and a bunch of questionnaires
that he'll be rolling through. So we can
try to get a handle on like how does
that work in a team setting and and does
it even make a difference? We uh we did
a a jet lag travel study with uh Bill
Kramer. Mhm. At University of
Connecticut. They did a bunch of stuff
in stores. We took blood performance.
They flew out to LA, did a whole bunch
of this stuff, flew them back out there,
retested them again. We did that
probably 15 years ago or something like
that. And that was a very fun study. So
uh I'm looking forward to see what you
guys pull up. Yeah. Yeah, me It's just
it's kind of a it it deals with things
we're interested in and um but again, we
got a a a student driving driving the
train on something that deals with human
performance in an area that's relevant
and I think people will be interested in
it. Well, what's really interesting is
if you follow college sports at all, you
realize that a trip from Florida to
California is now the same conference.
That's ACC. That's ACC. We are now in
the Big 10. I'm like my friend and I
were actually my brother-in-law Josh
were joking. He's an Ohio State guy and
uh he texted me something about
University of Washington and USC just
played in a classic Big 10 matchup and I
was just like like he's rubbing it in.
Changing. It's killing me. So this is a
this is a real part of collegiate
athletics and it's not just football.
Yeah. All of them. The other thing is to
consider is like they're they're doing
all of that and then having to maintain
classes. Oh my gosh. And then play again
at home. And I think the stress on these
student athletes is pretty tremendous
that we don't often give them a lot of
credit for because you see them on TV or
you're watching them play and it's like,
oh, they just play. They don't need to
go to class, but a lot of them do care
about class and it's it's a it's a big
big stress to do that kind of travel.
Folks that are paying attention are
spending a lot of time at the collegiate
level on sleep because of those things
and we expect them to go back and and
not, you know, make bad decisions and
all that stuff despite the fact that we
know what happens not only with lack of
sleep but just timing of sleep. Um, so
really cool
stuff. I'm gonna finish on one point and
I'm doing this intentionally at the end
here because I think it's really
important there. A lot of people will
talk about the current field of
nutrition and supplementation and
perhaps the conflicts of interest and
biases and can you trust the research
with and that's probably fair, right?
the general attitude is less trust in
the institutions and perhaps has ever
been and that's fine but I really wanted
to talk to you about this because I
don't know necessarily anybody who has
more industry funding uh you have been
your studies have been paid for by
supplement companies and you have gotten
money from the government NH and and
plenty of other places that said as we
have shown the entire conversation here
you're 5050 50, right? You clearly don't
hesitate that's generous to take to take
funding from somebody and then tell them
their product did not work. Yeah. I you
see that so much, you know, especially
with the rise of people bickering on
social media and stuff and it's
um at least in my world of academics. I
can't even take a grant from a company
that we don't get full rights to publish
every single thing we find. Those
contracts don't happen anymore. Maybe
that used to happen, but I don't know
anyone who has contracts like that. A
big research university. I mean, there
those are unfavorable terms. You cannot
do that. Like my job depends upon
publishing and the university can't
accept the money for me to administer
the grant, you know, and carry it out if
there's any terms that don't allow full
rights to to the data. Um, and so I
think that's largely I understand it
obviously.
Um, but in in my experience, it's really
hard to get these grants, especially
with a reputation like ours where it's
like I think they come to us because if
it works, I think that it can be
trusted.
Um, and if it doesn't work, I'm going to
tell you it doesn't work. And then my
goal would be that a company would take
that in stride and say, "Well, let me
improve it." It doesn't always work that
way. And you know, some relationships, I
don't know, you they just amicably end.
But but but you know, really our goal is
to just do the best work we possibly
can. And then your intention of this
question is good because
you can trust the data, but I think you
also have to look at the lab and the
university and the lead author and the
corresponding author and like you have
to have sort of a a skill set to make
sure that the data look great. And even
then, you're not always 100% guaranteed
for sure because there's biases that
exist everywhere. But by and large, you
can basically put to rest that
someone's missing with all the data just
to make sure that they publish what the
company wants. I can't even take those
grants at all. Yeah.
So, is it
fair, and I'm clearly asking this in a
directional way
here, for someone to pull up a
study, look at the conflicts of interest
statement, see that it's been funded by
a company, and then immediately throw
those data out to immediately assume
that this was biased and bought and paid
for by the study. By my tone, you can
clearly see my position there. Yeah.
Yeah. Not not at all. Uh that is not
that is not fair. Um I mean some of the
best work that exists would never come.
And if you want answers about these
supplement questions, every study you've
ever done, somebody has to do it and
someone has to fund it. They're
expensive. Yeah.
And you're not going to get some of this
kind of funding unless there's a disease
state from some of the federal agencies,
right? And even then it's harder to get
in that realm. Um, and so if you want
those data, you have to get it from a
company that has something that is
invested in it. They make the product,
they want to produce the product. Yeah.
In the best examples that I've been a
part of, people have approached you
early before something's designed and
that's rare. Most times it exists
already and then they make enough money
to then fund research. So then they can
try it. Um, and then in some cases these
companies um, do really well. Sometimes
they'll fold, sometimes they change
their marketing strategy. Um, sometimes
they'll change a dosing strategy. I
think what would be really helpful would
be saying when you look at papers and
you see that it's been funded by a
supplement company, you I know you're
going to look at the lab and you'll know
the people on there and you'll know the
students and the faculty and the
institution. It makes it easy for people
like you and I to quickly vet that. So,
I can look at things and go, "Yeah, I'm
not believing that yet." I see it's
funded by the company. Okay. one of the
co-authors works with the company and I
don't recognize that
lab doesn't mean it's wrong or fake at
all, but I'm going to have much more
hesitation. Right. For people that don't
know labs, they don't know who you are.
You know, the one of the most dedicated
or published prolific people in this
area, they don't know the labs. Are
there anything you can give them to
help? Because it is also real. If you
see there is people who have straight up
fraudulent in data, there people who
have made studies up. Uh I use actually
I don't know I'm not familiar with
retraction watch. It's great. It's a
great place where you can see papers
that are retracted. Awesome service. So
that stuff does happen. It's not really
common, but it gets the headlines. But
it gets the headlines, right? Makes
people scared. So it's true. When I
personally see a study that's been
funded by a certain Okay. Like I'm
notching it in my brain as datim. That's
an important datim. Doesn't mean
anything, but it is a nice little datim.
Any advice for people that are trying to
navigate that because we don't want them
looking at papers, not looking at
conflicts of interest at all are not
looking at potential funding sources. We
want them to. That's good. But how do
they not overreact as well? Yeah. Yeah.
I think there's two approaches to it. Um
I actually don't know a ton of people
who will be searching PubMed like you or
I might for these papers. And so if
you're looking at a whole like a product
and I would look at how the product's
tested, the label, you know, the third
party testing that exists for some of
the actual supplements and you probably
have covered some of that before. It's
like it's it's an interesting place to
be. And you the companies have to do a
ton of work to get those certifications,
particularly for sport. um certified for
sport informed choice
NSF those are really expensive and
really hard and and there's different
uses for them and so people can um say
what they want sort of about the back
and forth but those are what currently
are trusted and they're the ones are
getting into like universities and these
other things so so that's an important
sort of distinction. Um, an easy way is
some resources like examine.com where
people can look up the individual
ingredients, see what other u papers
have been published on it. They get sort
of a a grade on it. And then if you're
actually reading the paper, I think
you're going to have to then say, okay,
who wrote that paper and just search
that person's name again and see if you
can come up with any other things that
you're seeing as a pattern in that
space. Um, yeah. Okay. So fair enough to
say those things are important to pay
attention to but on its surface doesn't
immediately throw out 100%. I mean yeah
that if you want these things to be
researched we need funding sources.
Yeah. And if it wants to be 100%
independent then please ping our
research account because we can run
those studies.
Yeah. Any philanthropic donor out there
that wants to pay for all these things,
right? Uh Mike has an account that you
can send all $300 million to. Right.
Yeah. Amazing, man. Uh, anything else
you feel like we've missed from earlier
that you're going to go back and say or
any other awesome stuff you want to
share with people? No, I mean, I think
we we covered quite a lot. I I I uh I
hope we didn't get sort of lost in the
weeds on some of it, but for me, it's
really important to share that you can
have a pretty fulfilling career and
fulfilling life doing what you love to
do. Um, and you just have to find the
right outlet for it, you know? And
that's sort of the passion we're trying
to share with all of this is, um, how
can we sort of get human performance to
a place that is mainstream and how can
we answer these questions that people
ask? And, uh, I I hope that if anything
from this, you can kind of see that the
work we're putting out there is um, I
hope going to lead sort of the change in
that in that sort of mindset and shift
on how we view these types of studies.
Yeah, I I'm I'm sure that will have the
impact. I I can tell just by the way
that you've talked today. Uh you didn't
have a direct path to your career. You
bounced around a little bit and I know
you toyed with the industry for a while
and did some other things and it's not
always necessarily this you woke up when
you one day when you were 12 and
realized you wanted to become a sports
scientist. No, did not happen that way.
A dietician, whatever else. Um, but the
the way that you educate, I know that as
I mentioned a couple times now and I've
seen you speak at multiple events,
you're a phenomenal educator. Uh, you've
earned many awards in those areas. You
have courses that are available for
people. Yes. That they tell us about
that. Yeah. So, we had a venture a while
back to to uh create basically an
academic course but for everyday people.
It's uh 24 30 minute lectures. It was
put out by a company called The Great
Courses at the time. got picked up by
Wrium. Um, but that's it's if you're
like interested in a classroom kind of a
setting, that's that's what it is. It's
it's designed for everyday people, but
everything you want to know about um
it's called Changing Body Composition
Through Diet and Exercise. So, it's not
all that sexy of a title, but it it
tells you what you're going to get.
Yeah. And so, that's available. Anyone
can go take that. Yes. Yeah. That's uh
don't have to be enrolled in Florida
State University, anything like that.
No, no, that's like on Amazon and other
places. Yeah. Yep. They can Google that
around and find that. We'll have show
links in the show notes of course to all
those things over there. I mentioned it
earlier but please tell them how they
can come to your lab uh offering
metabolic testing and body composition
how all that works and where they go.
Our pay for testing services basically
anybody can have access to the research
grade equipment that we use. It's a sort
of a win-win for everybody. You get a
great experience in our in our
institute. Um, the equipment stays
continually used, which is how it works,
better than worse. The service fees, as
Andy mentioned, are reasonable. Um, and
so that's just all through. I think I
looked and it was like
$50 for some of the testing. $75 like
very, very, very reasonable. It is. It's
quite reasonable. And they have great
packages and I we have a outreach
director, Kieran Patterson, now who's
running that part of it. And we have uh
students involved. So, you give everyone
kind of a good experience. Oh, right.
Yeah. And it's just it's just great. We
we have even have like dietary
counseling and services like that that
are available. So a lot of the I tell
you it's everybody. We've had 14year-old
athletes that are on their way up to
Olympic caliber to 75year-old
individuals who heard they should add a
little bit of muscle. Um and so everyone
in between sort of um showing up to see
what we've got over there. It's a it's a
good spot. And where do they find that?
Where do they go to see that? And that's
just on the website for the lab which is
ism
uh.fsu.edu. you. Gotcha. Okay. And
again, we'll have links to all that
stuff. Man, I can't appreciate and thank
you enough for coming all the way out
here. I appreciate the time. I
appreciate you've everything you've done
on the field and how much you've shared
uh with us here today. I know that
there's a ton of useful information
here. I know that you shared a bunch of
information that most people have never
heard before or is counter to what they
thought they knew. And I think we're
going to hear plenty of stories of
success after this. So, thank you so
much, man. You're welcome, Andy.
Appreciate it. Thank you for joining
today's episode with Dr. Mike Ormsby. If
you'd like to learn more about Mike's
work or you're interested in supporting
his research at Florida State, please
see the links in our show notes. Right
now, Mike and his lab have a dollar to
dollar match going, so anyone who makes
contributions will have it matched up to
$50,000. An excellent opportunity to
support highquality and helpful
research. Mike also has educational
courses that anyone in the world can
take as well as social media, so you can
follow him there on Instagram and
Twitter as great places to learn more
and keep up to date with the work he's
doing and his institute. Thank you for
joining for today's episode. My goal, as
always, is to share exciting scientific
insights that help you perform at your
best. If the show resonates with you and
you want to help ensure this information
remains free and accessible to anyone in
the world, there are a few ways that you
can support. First, you can subscribe to
the show on YouTube, Spotify, and Apple.
And on Apple, and Spotify, you can leave
us up to a five-star review. Subscribing
and leaving a review really does help us
a lot. Also, please check out our
sponsors. The show would not exist
without them and their exceptional
products and services. Finally, you can
share today's episode with a friend who
you think would enjoy it. If you have
any content questions or suggestions,
please put those in the comment section
on YouTube. I really do try my best to
read them all and to see what you have
to say. I use my Instagram and
ex-profiles also exclusively for
scientific communication. So those are
great places to follow along for more
learning. My handle is Dr. Andy Galpin
on both platforms. We also have an email
newsletter that distills all of our
episodes in the most actionable
takeaways. We have newsletters on how to
improve fitness in V2 max, how to build
muscle and strength, and much more. To
subscribe to the newsletter, just go to
performpodcast.com and click newsletter.
It's completely free and we do not share
your email with anybody. Thank you for
listening and never forget in the famous
words of Bill Bowererman, if you have a
body, you are an athlete.